<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Raptazure&#39;s Space</title>
  
  <subtitle>&quot;Non merita nome di creatore, se non Iddio ed il Poeta.&quot;</subtitle>
  <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-07-13T12:54:26.746Z</updated>
  <id>http://raptazure.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Raptazure</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>从海德格尔的锤子到隐喻的戏剧性</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/07/12/ooo-tools/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/07/12/ooo-tools/</id>
    <published>2025-07-11T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-07-13T12:54:26.746Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<h3 id="碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子"><a href="#碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子" class="headerlink" title="碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子"></a>碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子</h3><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a3f358cb8da5c8a805da.webp"></p><p>深夜，万籁俱寂，你走到相伴多年的桌子前，将海德格尔的《存在与时间》平摊在上面。这桌子的一切都显得那么熟悉：你知道木头上每道花纹的行迹，你知道每一处不小心洒上的墨汁的残体。而此时，你对桌子本身并无兴趣，而是试图穷尽面前书本世界中蕴含的奥秘。你的胳膊支撑在桌子上，桌子的存在显得那么理所当然，它的功能性已经占据了你对其认知的主体，其他的特质都在漫漫黑夜中隐退不见，此刻留存的，只有你与哲学。</p><span id="more"></span><p>然而，正当沉浸书本之时，未知的神秘却突然攻击了你，这是属于“物”的神秘——桌子的一条腿突然碎掉了！随着桌板的下落，你险些给面前的书磕了个头，可比起这物理上的连锁反应，你更多感觉到的是惊讶、不解、甚至恐惧。属于真实桌子的一角在你的意识中留下了新的印记：在桌腿破碎的一瞬，你发现了桌子在除其工具性与表面花纹之外的另一个存在维度，它隐退的一角又在你的心中显现。</p><p>看着这变了形的桌子，你不禁想到了刚刚读到的海德格尔的锤子：当锤子被熟练使用时，它是“透明”的工具，使用者无需思考锤子的属性，而是直接用它敲钉子——此时锤子作为“用具”融入了实践（即“在世界之中存在”），物在此隐退（withdraw），其“用具性”显现。然而，当锤子损坏，物先前隐退的一角从实践背景中“突显”，反抗着人类为其施加的纯粹工具性，展示着其存在中仍未被知晓的无限。</p><p>而这也是面向物的本体论（Object-Oriented Ontology）之中所说物的“隐退”（withdrawal）：无论在理论还是在实践中，物体都无法被其与人类或其他物体的关系所穷尽，所有的物自体（thing-in-itself）在交互中都彼此隐退，它们之间的每一种关系都是一种翻译行为，而不是对其全部本质的呈现。为了便于讨论物在不同关系中其本身以及感官特质间的交互关系，哈曼将物分为两个层次——实在的物（real objects）与感官的物（sensual objects）：实在的物即康德所说的物自体，是从日常的经验世界中隐退的存在，正如永远不露真身、只是悬垂下恐怖的克苏鲁；而感官的物则存在于经验世界中，作为物自体的投射，可以被其他人或物感知，正如桌子上延展的木纹。与对物的分类对应，哈曼也区分了两种属性——实在属性（real qualities）与感官属性（sensual qualities）：实在属性对应实在的物，需通过智性探索才可能触及，而感官属性对应感官的物，即在经验中呈现的属性。</p><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a45e58cb8da5c8a808b0.png"></p><p>那么，在认识到物的隐退、完成了方便讨论的分类之后，我们不禁会问，这和隐喻的戏剧性有什么关系？不要着急，接下来，先让我们看看艺术创作与审美过程中 RO 与 SQ 发生的奇妙反应。<br><br></p><h3 id="艺术与实在的物"><a href="#艺术与实在的物" class="headerlink" title="艺术与实在的物"></a>艺术与实在的物</h3><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a4c458cb8da5c8a80b72.jpg"></p><p>正如华兹华斯在 <em>Lines Composed a Few Miles above Tintern Abbey</em> 中所写，“While with an eye made quiet by the power &#x2F; Of harmony, and the deep power of joy, &#x2F; We see into the life of things”，哈曼延续奥尔特加的观点，认为艺术可以让我们深潜至隐退于经验世界中的实在之物，将华兹华斯所说的“life of things”呈现在我们心中。用哈曼的术语讲，艺术是实在的物（RO）与感官体验（SQ）的“张力与融合”，不同于日常经验中 SO-SQ 理所应当的顺畅贴合，也不同于纯粹藏匿的 RO-RQ 与现实之间的断裂，这种 RO-SQ 的交互关系，使艺术在可见的感性领域与背后的藏匿实在之间形成了永恒的张力。</p><p>而这也与我们日常的审美与创作体验相吻合。当我们凝视梵高的《农鞋》，内心所感受到的并不仅仅是日常经验中作为工具的鞋，而是一个更加隐秘与更加真实的存在，仿佛在画作中看到了“鞋的生命”。梵高用颜料与画笔，通过描绘他眼中鞋的存在，展现出了其所栖居的一个不同世界，将某个未曾注意的隐蔽存在从工具性的日常中显影。</p><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a58858cb8da5c8a810b5.jpg"></p><p>可是，这个在艺术中显影的隐蔽存在真的是鞋子的真实本身吗？既然之前，我们提到过，物与物交互时，实在的物对于彼此都是隐退的，不管我们多么努力地思索、感知，实在的物在某种程度上都不可完全触及，那么在此时显露的实在之物又是什么呢？下面，就该是戏剧的开演了。<br><br></p><h3 id="隐喻的戏剧性"><a href="#隐喻的戏剧性" class="headerlink" title="隐喻的戏剧性"></a>隐喻的戏剧性</h3><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a5f558cb8da5c8a81398.jpg"></p><p>在看到隐喻“松树是死去的火苗”后，我们的第一反应大概会是：这个隐喻将火苗的某些特征（例如形状）与松树这实在之物建立了某种联系，从而赋予了或者说揭开了松树在日常的感官体验中隐退的某些特质。然而，正如我们在上一节的末尾所说，不管是多少华丽的隐喻都不能完全照亮松树本身隐秘的存在山洞，而只能点亮其中的一角，也就是说，作为物自体的松树在这个交互过程中依旧是保持隐退的。</p><p>虽然松树在隐喻面前神秘依旧，留下的却不是深不可测的虚无。隐喻中的火苗仍热切地寻找着与物相拥，因为只有当火苗的特质与某个物体结合，隐喻才能真正地存在。那么，此时的“物”又由什么来充当呢？哈曼在 <em>Object-Oriented Ontology</em> 中给出了一个让人眼前一亮的答案——我们读者自己。是的，即使松树本身于我们的思考、感知、隐喻之中都持续隐退，但在我们艺术的体验中，有一种物自体持续在场，那就是我们自己。在对隐喻的体验中，我们作为 RO 替代了不在场的松树，而拥有了“死去的火苗”的特质，此时此刻，我们不再是一个置身境外的旁观者，而是将自己作为读者的存在融入了隐喻的审美体验之中——我们正在出演一场无人观赏的戏剧，出演的角色则是本身又在扮演已逝火苗的松树；用更流行的话说，我们在隐喻的体验之中，完成了一场对于 cosplay 的 cosplay。是的，在这个隐喻之中，作为松树出演的我们，就是真正的物自体。</p><p>再让我们用一个例子结合图示来明晰这个过程。古希腊诗人荷马曾在《伊利亚特》与《奥德赛》中将大海称为“黑酒之海”（wine-dark sea, οἶνοψ πόντος），在这个隐喻中，通过将新的感官特质（SQ）“黑酒性”施加到“海”之上，先前日常经验中的深蓝之海已无法承担这想象力的透视（下图 SQ 的划去），而由于“海”的物自体总是无限隐退（下图 RO 旁的叹号），这感官特质（SQ）只能与另一种物自体（RO）建立联系，也就是隐喻的体验者与表演者——此时出演大海的我们。</p><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a42f58cb8da5c8a8077a.png"><br><br></p><h3 id="Coda"><a href="#Coda" class="headerlink" title="Coda"></a>Coda</h3><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a63058cb8da5c8a81530.jpg"></p><p>每一个隐喻，都是一个小小的剧场；每一次审美体验，都是一次崭新的出演。在艺术欣赏之中，我们不断替代着那无限隐退的神秘之物，在全身心的表演之中成为了必不可缺的物自体。拿着海德格尔坏掉的锤子走来，我们静静伫立在一幅画作、一个隐喻面前，看到了那抗拒一切窥视的神秘。此时，兀自隐退的物自体像一面神奇的镜子，将在表演中显露的“真实”无比明亮地映射在我们的心田。</p><p>由此我们得知，美所潜藏的奥秘，终将在每个人的出演中升起。正如济慈所言：</p><blockquote><p>“Away! away! for I will fly to thee,<br>Not charioted by Bacchus and his pards,<br>But on the viewless wings of Poesy”</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;&ensp;—— Ode to a Nightingale</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;h3 id=&quot;碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;碎掉的桌子与海德格尔的锤子&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a3f358cb8da5c8a805da.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;深夜，万籁俱寂，你走到相伴多年的桌子前，将海德格尔的《存在与时间》平摊在上面。这桌子的一切都显得那么熟悉：你知道木头上每道花纹的行迹，你知道每一处不小心洒上的墨汁的残体。而此时，你对桌子本身并无兴趣，而是试图穷尽面前书本世界中蕴含的奥秘。你的胳膊支撑在桌子上，桌子的存在显得那么理所当然，它的功能性已经占据了你对其认知的主体，其他的特质都在漫漫黑夜中隐退不见，此刻留存的，只有你与哲学。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>威廉·布莱克的四种视界</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/07/08/blake-four-visions/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/07/08/blake-four-visions/</id>
    <published>2025-07-07T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-07-13T12:52:37.334Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a89a58cb8da5c8a8195f.jpg" alt="William_Blake_by_Thomas_Phillips.jpg"></p><p>威廉·布莱克 (1757-1827) ，英国著名诗人、画家。提到布莱克，很多人的第一反应大概会是《天真与经验之歌》中的短诗 <em>The Tyger</em> 与 Hubert Parry 谱曲的 <em>Jerusalem</em>，无论是那明亮燃于黑夜之林的灵魂之虎，与那关于创造与神明震慑人心的诘问，还是那机械僵硬、可能寄居在每个人心中的 Satanic Mills，与那在艺术的熔炉中滚烫前进的 Chariots of Fire，都让布莱克成为了英语文学中属于永恒的诗人。</p><span id="more"></span><p>然而，他创作生涯后期统称为“预言书”（Prophetic Books）的很多作品，却因其神话系统的复杂度成为了 Northrop Frye 所说的“what is in proportion to its merits the least read body of poetry in the English language”，其中蕴藏的许多珍宝只为少数人所了解。在一系列的 Illuminated Books 中，布莱克提及了四种认知世界的方式，分别对应与世界的四种关系，即 Ulro，Generation，Beulah，Eternity。这个系统在接下来的200年里，不断证明着其价值，在时代的变迁中保留着无尽的活力，为人们提供了一个清晰且实用的认知框架。今天，就让我们走进这四种视界，了解布莱克庞大思想系统中的灿烂一角。<br><br></p><h2 id="世界的一个切片"><a href="#世界的一个切片" class="headerlink" title="世界的一个切片"></a>世界的一个切片</h2><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a8b358cb8da5c8a81964.jpg" alt="Newton-WilliamBlake.jpg"></p><p>首先，在了解布莱克的世界之前，我们先要打破预设的认知模式，也即主客体对立的 Cartesian Division，将世界的破碎切片重新拼成一个整体。灵魂与肉体、主观与客观、认知与存在的分离，从柏拉图与亚里士多德开始就贯穿了西方哲学史，直到笛卡尔提出“Cogito ergo sum”，以及后续唯心主义与唯物主义的对立，这种 Cartesian Division 似乎已变成了世界的既定事实。然而，在布莱克的系统中，这只是认识世界的一个侧面或切片，并不意味着“真实”的全部。这种认识方式特征是将世界二分为“我”或者“灵魂”，即观察的主体，以及“非我”或者“物质”，即被观察的客体，以此来理解我们的日常经验世界，也为科学的发展提供一个稳定的理论框架。</p><p>然而，如果我们更加细化地思考不同存在状态下二者的关系，结论似乎并没有这么简单：有时，我们的世界只剩下一个狭隘的主体，完全淹没在自己的思绪中而不见世界，时而追溯回过去永远不可能再去拯救的深渊，时而延展到未来永远在延展的不确定性与焦虑，此时的我们，作为孤立于世界的存在，已经完全消解了任何客体，将意识牢牢囚禁在自己理性的头颅里；而有时，当我们沉浸于爱情的甜蜜，或者全心用想象力编织一个崭新的世界，主客体的界限似乎不再那么明显，而意识也随着界限的消弭而不断扩张，将更广的世界、甚至整个宇宙都包含为一个整体，直到万物与我齐一。是的，笛卡尔所发现的，也许只是世界的一个切片，而真正的世界，远比那二元对立的简单逻辑更为广阔：当我们的视角转变，世界也随之转动，此时我们的“感知”也就等同于“存在”，“主体”同时也变为“客体”，二者不再分离，这也是弥尔顿在《失乐园》中所写的“The mind is its own place, and in itself can make a heaven of hell, a hell of heaven”, 以及布莱克所言“The eye altering alters all”的含义。由此，在将破碎的世界拼为整体之时，布莱克的四种认知的方式也变成了四种存在的模式，在错综复杂的当代社会投下明亮清晰的投影。<br><br></p><h2 id="单维视界（Single-Vision-Ulro）"><a href="#单维视界（Single-Vision-Ulro）" class="headerlink" title="单维视界（Single Vision - Ulro）"></a>单维视界（Single Vision - Ulro）</h2><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a7c358cb8da5c8a8193a.jpg"></p><p>灰烬、黑暗、孤立，这是属于单维视界的沉寂之地，无生命之物是这个世界的典型存在。在单维视界里，所留存的只有“我”的头颅，或者说，只有无穷的客体。</p><p>当一个人陷入绝对孤立的沉思，当他垂目水面却只爱上自己形体的倒影，当他耳中听到的只有无尽的回声，当错综复杂的存在之网被撕裂为一根丝线，单维视界就此显现，其最突出的特质就是抽象（Abstraction）。当我们把具体的感官体验或者 Qualia 抽象为一个僵死的概念，并基于这种概念进行各种运算，由此渴望了解关于存在的本质，我们的视野就无限缩小，将世界的本质都收束在微不足道的一具头骨之中。正如布莱克的画作 <em>Ancient of Days</em> 里使用圆规丈量存在的创世之神，正如灾难之后将生命简化为无生命数字的新闻播报，正如沉浸于社交媒体各种贩卖焦虑的信息而失去了自己的主体感知，我们的<strong>体验</strong>被<strong>抽象</strong>淹没，所留下的只有连锁的祛魅（Disenchantment），无止境的受困，与充满绝望的生存。这时我们对于时间的体验反转，Clock Time 成为永恒的反义，成为无限延展的痛苦刑具，正如但丁笔下的地狱。<br><br></p><h2 id="二维视界（Twofold-Vision-Generation）"><a href="#二维视界（Twofold-Vision-Generation）" class="headerlink" title="二维视界（Twofold Vision - Generation）"></a>二维视界（Twofold Vision - Generation）</h2><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a8ce58cb8da5c8a81966.jpg" alt="Ff107540.jpg"></p><p>生长、枯萎、轮回，这是属于二维视界的喧嚣与争斗，植物是这个世界的典型存在。正如其名字 Generation，这个世界即是我们日常所经历的属于主体与客体、灵魂与身体、生长与枯萎的世界。</p><p>在二维视界里，春夏秋冬一刻不停地进行着循环，万物发芽、生长、成熟之后又逐渐走向枯萎，溪流蒸发成为云朵，云朵又成为雨水返回溪流。这个世界最显著的特点即为雪莱所言的可变性（Mutability），在这里，喜悦随时可能远离，而悲伤亦是如此；鲜花可能于明日继续绽放，也可能在席卷的寒风下凋落。生活在 Generation 中的人可以称为“自然的人”，他是卢梭所言的 Noble Savage，是达尔文系统中的与环境相适应的人。从某种程度上说，这个世界是属于“自然”的世界。<br><br></p><h2 id="三维视界-（Threefold-Vision-Beulah）"><a href="#三维视界-（Threefold-Vision-Beulah）" class="headerlink" title="三维视界 （Threefold Vision - Beulah）"></a>三维视界 （Threefold Vision - Beulah）</h2><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a94658cb8da5c8a8198a.jpg" alt="but161.1.1.wc.300.jpg"></p><p>美梦、沉醉、休憩，这是属于三维视界的理想与纯真，爱人是这个世界的典型存在。Beulah 是人类用爱在自然之中筑造的花园，是一个可以称为家的地方。</p><p>在某种程度上说，这是《创世纪》中人类原初的伊甸，是亚当与夏娃曾经劳作的地方，而花园中的两棵树——善恶之树与生命之树，也分别对应着向下与向上的两种视界，即 Generation 与 Eternity。因为现实的饥饿总会不时到来，而人们总会吃下善恶之果或生命之果，这个视界更偏向于一种过渡的状态。在这个世界里，经过第三种元素——“爱”的调和，主体与客体的界限在此处消解，他们此时都拥有了同一个名字，他们都成为了“爱人”。在父母对婴孩的关爱之中，在热烈的相拥与亲吻之中，在对某项事业的热爱之中，三维的视界就此展开，在自然无止境的纷争中铺开安静休憩的空间，让人们得以进入甜蜜的梦乡。<br><br></p><h2 id="四维视界（Fourfold-Vision-Eternity）"><a href="#四维视界（Fourfold-Vision-Eternity）" class="headerlink" title="四维视界（Fourfold Vision - Eternity）"></a>四维视界（Fourfold Vision - Eternity）</h2><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a97558cb8da5c8a819a1.jpg" alt="jerusalem.e.p100.300.jpg"></p><p>永恒、熔炉、想象，这是属于四维视界的创造与无限，诗人是这个视界的典型存在。在三维视界“爱”的基础上，这个视界则引入了第四种存在，即“创造”。</p><p>通过艺术与想象，艺术家所视之物不仅成为了所爱之物，也成为了所创造之物，意义在此之中持续诞生，正如雪莱在《为诗辩护》中所言，“Non merita nome di creatore, se non Iddio ed il Poeta”，最初的神灵在这个世界显现。在四维视界里，主客体的界限已经模糊不见，在创造的烈火煅烧熔铸之后，一切留存的，都成为了一座座高耸于城市之中的尖塔，显示着人类创造力的无限可能。在这座城市里，留存着人类所有真正的文明，闪耀着人类所有真正的辉光，这里是真正的“永恒之城”，也即布莱克所说的 Golgonooza。<br><br></p><h2 id="攀登之梯"><a href="#攀登之梯" class="headerlink" title="攀登之梯"></a>攀登之梯</h2><p><img src="https://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/e/ea/Blake_jacobsladder.jpg/960px-Blake_jacobsladder.jpg" alt="Blake_jacobsladder.jpg"></p><p>从 Ulro 沙石的沉睡世界中苏醒，我们归于自然，而爱（将客体转变为所爱之物）以及艺术（将客体转变为所创造之物）将我们分别带入原初的花园与永恒的城市，在那里，太阳已然不再是如铜钱般的闪亮圆盘，而是亿万天使歌唱圣歌之处。</p><blockquote><p>Now I a fourfold vision see,<br>And a fourfold vision is given to me;<br>‘Tis fourfold in my supreme delight<br>And threefold in soft Beulah’s night<br>And twofold Always. May God us keep<br>From Single vision &amp; Newton’s sleep!</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6873a89a58cb8da5c8a8195f.jpg&quot; alt=&quot;William_Blake_by_Thomas_Phillips.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;威廉·布莱克 (1757-1827) ，英国著名诗人、画家。提到布莱克，很多人的第一反应大概会是《天真与经验之歌》中的短诗 &lt;em&gt;The Tyger&lt;/em&gt; 与 Hubert Parry 谱曲的 &lt;em&gt;Jerusalem&lt;/em&gt;，无论是那明亮燃于黑夜之林的灵魂之虎，与那关于创造与神明震慑人心的诘问，还是那机械僵硬、可能寄居在每个人心中的 Satanic Mills，与那在艺术的熔炉中滚烫前进的 Chariots of Fire，都让布莱克成为了英语文学中属于永恒的诗人。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Half Mocking and Half Plaintive Calls</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/06/04/the-loons/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/06/04/the-loons/</id>
    <published>2025-06-03T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-06-04T14:15:44.196Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6840538858cb8da5c82cddfd.png"></p><p>&ensp;&ensp;Near the end of <em>The Loons</em>, Vanessa notes that the “long-drawn call” of the birds, described as “half mocking and half plaintive”, has fallen silent across the lake, paralleling Piquette’s tragic death. This loss of sound seems to suggest that the birds and the Métis are destined to share a fate of bitter destruction. However, throughout the passage, if one listens closely, the author’s tone echoes that same mix of mockery and lament. By ridiculing her own deeply ingrained arrogance and indifference toward the Métis and by mourning the oppression and injustice suffered by people like Piquette, the author deconstructs her own racist narrative rather than reinforcing it. What might seem like a racist text is transformed into a sorrowful confession.</p><span id="more"></span><p>&ensp;&ensp;To decide whether a text is racist, we can use a simple criterion: is the critique aimed at the marginalized groups themselves, or is it directed at the marginalizing behaviors of those in power? The former marks a racist text, while the latter marks an anti-racist one. Some critics might argue that emphasizing the tragic fate of the Métis, as a result of white people’s unfair treatment, ends up victimizing them and undermining their strength. However, when one looks at historical records of witch hunts or the atrocities committed by Hitler against the Jews, where the focus is on condemning the tyrants and not beautifying the lives of victims, it becomes increasingly clear that such portrayals are meant to indict the causes of suffering, not to reinforce a static image of victimhood.</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;The subtlety of Laurence’s writing lies in her highly self-conscious choice of the narrative focus, itself mirroring the very process of marginalization. By centering the story on the white girl Vanessa and telling it through her perspective, Piquette’s voice is muted, her emotions concealed, and her story fragmented. This narrative choice, designed to appeal to a white audience (and hopefully make them reflect upon their own biases), reveals just how ingrained the racist lens is in dominant culture. At the same time, the author’s narrative voice is self-conscious and almost self-mocking, as can be seen in Vanessa’s reaction when she learns of Piquette’s impending marriage to an Englishman. It isn’t until then does Vanessa “really see her, for the first and only time in all the years”, that is, not until after Piquette has been assimilated into white society through marriage, at the risk of losing her cultural identity that the white protagonist begins to truly acknowledge her existence as a human being, despite the obvious fact that they had “both lived in the same town” since childhood.</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;By depicting Vanessa’s nearly dehumanizing indifference and blinding arrogance, the text achieves an ironic, almost comically tragic quality. In mocking Vanessa’s willful, almost hyperbolic blindness, the author is also critiquing the limitations of her own narrative strategy. It is only after this moment of “seeing” and self-mockery that the focus gradually shifts to Piquette. Sadly, this shift is triggered only by Piquette’s untimely death — in paragraphs 64 through 69, the story almost exclusively centers on her life, providing the most detailed and intense description of the entire passage, which only intensifies the tragedy, for it is already near the end of the story and definitely too late.</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;This parallel between content and structure reinforces the idea that the tragic fate of the loons, along with the suffering of Piquette and other Métis people, originates not only from the unfair treatment they endure in the story’s world, but also from the text’s own biased portrayal and silencing. Even the reader’s tendency to admire Vanessa and disdain Piquette reflects this dynamic. In this way, by marginalizing and silencing Piquette’s voice, the story becomes a self-critique: the author is not only condemning the marginalizing actions of white characters but is also questioning her own stylistic choices. In writing about the “half mocking and half plaintive” calls of the loons, the author is also expressing the half mocking and half plaintive attitude toward her own narration. In this sense, Laurence’s <em>The Loons</em> is truly anti-racist, in its own subtle but poignant way. </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6840538858cb8da5c82cddfd.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ensp;&amp;ensp;Near the end of &lt;em&gt;The Loons&lt;/em&gt;, Vanessa notes that the “long-drawn call” of the birds, described as “half mocking and half plaintive”, has fallen silent across the lake, paralleling Piquette’s tragic death. This loss of sound seems to suggest that the birds and the Métis are destined to share a fate of bitter destruction. However, throughout the passage, if one listens closely, the author’s tone echoes that same mix of mockery and lament. By ridiculing her own deeply ingrained arrogance and indifference toward the Métis and by mourning the oppression and injustice suffered by people like Piquette, the author deconstructs her own racist narrative rather than reinforcing it. What might seem like a racist text is transformed into a sorrowful confession.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Literary Wanderings</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/21/literary-wanderings/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/21/literary-wanderings/</id>
    <published>2025-05-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-21T15:05:31.582Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/682dea7858cb8da5c80357f2.jpg"></p><h1 id="Deviation"><a href="#Deviation" class="headerlink" title="Deviation"></a>Deviation</h1><p>Illness and the following recovery often herald the coming of the muses. Both symbolically and physically, these two states mark a deviation from the norm, from the routine, from the familiar, and essentially, according to Shelley’s A Defence of Poetry, possess a quality of poetry in the broader sense of the word. I remember having written a poem about the owl springing from the cage of frost when catching a fever brought by COVID-19; I also remember the ecstasy and vitality brought by recovery which accelerates the movements of the bouncing thoughts inside the skull. What Nietzsche famously wrote in The Gay Science, “Gratitude pours forth continually, as if the unexpected had just happened—the gratitude of a convalescent—for convalescence was unexpected…. The rejoicing of strength that is returning, of a reawakened faith in a tomorrow and the day after tomorrow, of a sudden sense and anticipation of a future, of impending adventures, of seas that are open again”, may indeed act as the source of inspiration, and the joy of life.</p><span id="more"></span><h1 id="Horticultural-Quietism"><a href="#Horticultural-Quietism" class="headerlink" title="Horticultural Quietism"></a>Horticultural Quietism</h1><p><em>Candide</em> of Voltaire:</p><p>The immense power of “cultivating our garden”, of “cultiver notre jardin” - to live in our own small plots instead of the heads of strangers, is extremely relevant in today’s world of flooding information. We need a project. It shouldn’t be too large or dependent on many people. The project should send us to sleep every night, weary but satisfied. It could be bringing up a child, writing a book, looking after a house, running a small shop, managing a little business, or, like the Turk in the book, tending to a few acres. This is the geographic modesty of Voltaire: he advises us to take just a few acres and make those your focus, to take a small orchard and grow lemons and apricots, to take some beds and grow asparagus and carrots, to cultivate a quiet garden that we can truly claim as our own.</p><h1 id="The-World-of-Things"><a href="#The-World-of-Things" class="headerlink" title="The World of Things"></a>The World of Things</h1><p>The Sensitive Plant serves as the medium between things and human, leaning towards the world of things; the Goddess serves as the same medium, only leaning towards the world of human → but to some extent, they all belong to the world of “things”, and not “human” in the sense of mortals → then, is the death of the Goddess a death of mortals, or essentially, a death of things?</p><h1 id="Misinterpretation"><a href="#Misinterpretation" class="headerlink" title="Misinterpretation"></a>Misinterpretation</h1><p>Misplaced interpretation is the violence against genuine literary understanding. How can one take a literary text out of the historical period it was composed in and merely use one’s imagination to haphazardly fill the gaping void between words and their meaning? Creative misreading certainly does not entail the reader’s fantasy can freely roam wherever it pleases, but is still constrained by contextual understanding. The textbook’s interpretation of Hazlitt’s comments on diction, claiming his essay fails to distinguish spoken language and written language by equalling the two, seems to me out of context and does a disservice to the original text, which essentially serves as a champagning essay for the everyday simple diction of the Romantic poetry, especially as exemplified in the Lyrical Ballads.</p><h1 id="Enchantment"><a href="#Enchantment" class="headerlink" title="Enchantment"></a>Enchantment</h1><p>“I’ll follow thee” - Hamlet, Keats</p><p>Hamlet follows his father’s ghost, and Keats  follows the nightingale’s song. </p><p>Hamlet descends into the “insanity” of revenge, and Keats enters into a fairy land forlorn.</p><p>Both enter another realm, another reality; both are enchanted.</p><p>“Of the chameleon’s dish I eat the air” → Shelley’s poet is from <em>Hamlet</em></p><h1 id="Chains-to-Change"><a href="#Chains-to-Change" class="headerlink" title="Chains to Change"></a>Chains to Change</h1><ul><li>Change in Form → poetic drama → focus more on the individual psyche (individual as the starting point)</li><li>From <em>Moira</em> to Moral Agency (the meaning of suffering → to actively forgive, not to passively bear)</li><li>From Power to Love (restraints symbolized by Kratos and Bia → leads to sacrifice (violence towards the self), which is the only way to defy the unchangeable order) (From violence to non-violence, from the physical to the mental&#x2F;spiritual)</li><li>From Tragic Pathos to Romantic Sublime (change in perception of history: from cyclic to progressive)</li><li>From Divine to Human</li></ul><h1 id="Reader-Response"><a href="#Reader-Response" class="headerlink" title="Reader-Response"></a>Reader-Response</h1><p>To practice teaching without students is like applying the reader-response theory to a text without an actual reader. By only imagining the act of someone reading, or in the teacher’s case, listening and responding, the receptor becomes a permanent void, a utilitarian means to help construct and maintain the predetermined structure of the lesson instead of an  end in itself. The receptor remains shapeless till the end, its only residence being the dim regions of the teacher’s egotistic mind. As a result, every action remains a presumption, or even worse, an assumption. In my opinion, the teaching skills truly required for a class, such as spontaneity, sympathy, openness and genuine care towards students can not really be improved through such a highly-wrought and performance-oriented staging of organized fantasy.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/682dea7858cb8da5c80357f2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;Deviation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Deviation&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Deviation&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Deviation&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Illness and the following recovery often herald the coming of the muses. Both symbolically and physically, these two states mark a deviation from the norm, from the routine, from the familiar, and essentially, according to Shelley’s A Defence of Poetry, possess a quality of poetry in the broader sense of the word. I remember having written a poem about the owl springing from the cage of frost when catching a fever brought by COVID-19; I also remember the ecstasy and vitality brought by recovery which accelerates the movements of the bouncing thoughts inside the skull. What Nietzsche famously wrote in The Gay Science, “Gratitude pours forth continually, as if the unexpected had just happened—the gratitude of a convalescent—for convalescence was unexpected…. The rejoicing of strength that is returning, of a reawakened faith in a tomorrow and the day after tomorrow, of a sudden sense and anticipation of a future, of impending adventures, of seas that are open again”, may indeed act as the source of inspiration, and the joy of life.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Literary Theory" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literary-Theory/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Walking Away from Omelas</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/15/walking-away-from-omelas/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/15/walking-away-from-omelas/</id>
    <published>2025-05-14T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-15T12:18:47.850Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6825dba258cb8da5c8f43c53.png"><br>Beneath the seemingly blissful everyday life of Omelas, there lies a gloomy truth – an innocent child, as the ultimate scapegoat, is bearing the crushing weight of the world in utter loneliness, just like that cursed titan Atlas in Greek mythology, the only difference being the vulnerable child has not rebelled against the vengeful gods. People who choose to stay in Omelas pass by this terror of injustice in silent acquiescence, relinquishing their human agency to make any meaningful ethical decision at all, and insisting that the single sinless child should somehow bear the whole weight of all their moral obligations. Can such a city still be called a utopia, where the goodness and beauty of humanity are cherished and celebrated, when every trace of happiness is sicklied over by the taint of injustice and bad faith?</p><span id="more"></span><p>We have two pieces of framing. First, we characterise “continuing to live in Omelas” as following the existing rules, that is, doing nothing about the child’s suffering. Because Omelas is a utopia characteristically defined by the suffering of a single child and the happiness of all the other citizens, thus changing this determining characteristic would be too radical that it would be no longer suitable to call the reformed city “Omelas” again – it would transform into another kind of utopia all together. Second, by “walking away”, we mean to shoulder our ethical responsibilities and moral agency as a human being again, to deny the justifiability of the innocent scapegoat, and to seek an alternative world, where perhaps everyone’s happiness can be achieved without the suffering of a sinless child, or where at least we can call the weight of our own moral decisions our own and become a truly agential human being.</p><p>We have three substantives. First, we argue that only by walking away from Omelas can people reclaim the full existential entailment of being a human. The dilemma in Omelas is not a mere calculation of lesser evils as exemplified by the famous trolley problem – it is inherently an existential inquiry. The city of Omelas is a predetermined paradise built upon predetermined cruelty, where the child is the only one responsible for all the citizens’ happiness, which the citizens are simply passively enjoying, without really being responsible for it; it is a place where suffering of the child has become not only a moral dilemma, but THE moral dilemma, simply because it is the single one that remains in Omelas – everything else is good and fine; it is a place where every ethical decision is boiled down into one known variable - the unconditional sacrifice of the innocent child, with all the other ethical complexities that being a human entails therefore completely eliminated. As a result, to relinquish the opportunity to act upon such a dilemma, i.e., to choose not to walk away, is to relinquish the possibility to lead an agential life all together; it is to prefer the comfort of a predetermined state of unchallenged perfection instead of embracing the reality of potentiality and freedom, where our ethical decisions can really be called our own, where we can claim “I am good because I have acted righteously”; it is to deny the inherent existential freedom and the corresponding responsibilities of being a human. According to the existential philosopher Jean Paul Satre, an essential part of being a human is exactly that “we are condemned to be free”, that is, at any given moment, we need to make decisions and then be responsible for the consequences of these decisions, which is seemingly a curse, but actually a blessing: the capacity to make hard, painful decisions and to learn from them is indispensable to our continued growth as moral beings. As a result, by walking away, we are refusing to accept such an abdication of moral duty; we are embracing the agency and freedom which is essential for being a human being, or rather, a “human becoming”; we are courageously shouldering the responsibility of shaping our own ethical destiny instead of passively accepting a predetermined sugar-coated injustice like a programmed robot. Comparatively speaking, those who choose to stay are ultimately running away from the pressure of a fully rounded agential life and are thus acting in “bad faith”: they are inherently denying their own freedom, favouring the predetermined ethical answer, merely to alleviate the crushing pressure of being human. The insidious feeling of moral complicity will haunt them after they have realised the inadequacy of such an action, because deep in their hearts, they know they have chosen comfort over conscience and freedom, stability over the heavy but essential burden of ethical decision-making, which makes us fully rounded human beings.</p><p>Second, we argue that only by walking away from Omelas can we begin to expect any possible improvement to happen upon the current situation. The city of Omelas, being a utopia, is by definition, trapped in a state of stasis, because by predefining the evil and the good, it has transcended the dialectical conflicts of history and ethics, becoming more like a concept instead of a city that is continually transforming and developing. According to the existential philosophers in the 19th and 20th centuries, the concept of utopia originates in our deep-rooted desire for stasis, and the existence of Omelas is exactly the fulfilment of our desire to exist in a stable and unchanging situation, which makes it even more alluring. But Ursula’s writing never explicitly states the impossibility of finding a better place in that particular universe, a place where all the happiness can still be enjoyed without the cruel practice of scapegoating. And she never explains the underlying mechanism that links the single child’s confinement with the whole world’s suffering, which makes the necessity of the suffering child rather dubious – maybe even without the child’s confinement, the world would still be fine? Maybe just like the ancient Greek festival Thargelia, the so-called sin-cleansing scapegoats are merely people’s invention to alleviate their own sense of guilt and responsibility? By walking away from Omelas, we are not only sending a symbolic message, but also proving it with our actions that we still believe there can be an alternative world where the “necessary evil” does not exist and we are ready to fight for this ideal, that we are willing to embrace the possibility of creating a new society despite the inherent uncertainty brought by change. Even in the worst scenario, where such an ideal remains nowhere to be found, we can still proudly claim that we prefer to reckon with the consequences of our own actions, to become fully responsible and agential as a human being, rather than passively accept a simplistic, unchanging state of “good” that potentially comes at the expense of our soul. Comparatively speaking, choosing to stay is to be forever trapped in the stasis defined by the very existence of Omelas; it is to live in quiet despair without the freedom or the agency to make the world a potentially better place; it is to surrender in happy ignorance without even trying to seek the alternative. Just like the prisoners in Plato’s cave, the citizens of Omelas, by choosing to forever stay in the cave, will never be able to enjoy the warmth of the sun. By remaining in the eternal stasis of seeming happiness, their disposition is essentially a hopeless one, because all potentialities have been eliminated.</p><p>Third, we argue that by walking away from Omelas, we are standing against the normalisation of cruelty and injustice and showing respect to the inherent dignity of each human being. The child’s suffering is far more than an abstract variable in a utilitarian equation; it is not a disposable cost that can be simply absorbed into a calculus of “the greater good”. Instead, that suffering child is living and breathing, just like every one of us. In fact, continuing to live in Omelas means that even your own child could become the scapegoat and bear the weight of the world in the future. What’s more, those who choose to stay are conveying a symbolic message that such systematic injustice, such a haphazard act of cruelty, is totally acceptable if it is for “the greater good”, that their collective happiness is inherently more valuable than the happiness of a single child. As this rule of scapegoating becomes solidified over time, systematic cruelty will be normalised, and people will fall into a pervasive pattern of moral apathy. In the long term, society might become so accustomed to sacrificing ethical standards for the so-called collective happiness that the distinction between right and wrong, just and unjust, beautiful and ugly will be blurred and compromised. Human history is replete with such bargains, such “necessary evil” that only leads to greater evil. For example, slavery was once thought by many as a “necessary evil”, which was indispensable for economic growth and the stability of the social order. The cruelty and injustice towards slaves were justified on utilitarian grounds: in many people’s eyes, the immense profits and rapid development brought by slavery simply outweighed the potential moral repugnance. However, in the long term, this “necessary evil” only led to more evils – it sown the seeds of systematic racism and civil unrest that still troubles many countries even today. By walking away from Omelas, we are saying the normalization and apathy towards cruelty is categorically false, no matter how “necessary” it may appear; we are saying the cost of a “perfect” society – when perfection is tainted with the blood of innocent children and the enforcement of systematic injustice - is too high a price for human dignity.</p><p>Therefore, we argue that walking away from the veiled terror of Omelas and trying to seek an alternative world is infinitely more preferable.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6825dba258cb8da5c8f43c53.png&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;Beneath the seemingly blissful everyday life of Omelas, there lies a gloomy truth – an innocent child, as the ultimate scapegoat, is bearing the crushing weight of the world in utter loneliness, just like that cursed titan Atlas in Greek mythology, the only difference being the vulnerable child has not rebelled against the vengeful gods. People who choose to stay in Omelas pass by this terror of injustice in silent acquiescence, relinquishing their human agency to make any meaningful ethical decision at all, and insisting that the single sinless child should somehow bear the whole weight of all their moral obligations. Can such a city still be called a utopia, where the goodness and beauty of humanity are cherished and celebrated, when every trace of happiness is sicklied over by the taint of injustice and bad faith?&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Debate" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Debate/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fragments of Thoughts - A Journey Downward and Upward</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/08/fragments-of-thoughts/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/08/fragments-of-thoughts/</id>
    <published>2025-05-07T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:46:10.598Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb3e658cb8da5c8e6665f.png"></p><h3 id="The-Downfall"><a href="#The-Downfall" class="headerlink" title="The Downfall"></a>The Downfall</h3><p>(2025.5.4) Every age has its own plight, and the relentless consumption of media is one of ours. In the vast expanse of cyberspace, many of us have succumbed to a peculiar kind of gluttony—a ceaseless craving perpetuated by the bombardment of video games, anime, provocative content, and endless streams of short videos. This insatiable beast, ever hungrier after feeding, has not only eaten away our time, but more importantly, our mind—our ability to concentrate is eroded, replaced by a constant pursuit of the new and the stimulating; the passage of time, once a steady flow, now feels disjointed and surreally fleeting; our experiences, once cohesively expanding throughout the day, have fragmented into foggy moments clouded by digital haze; creativity, the expression of the human spirit, lies dormant under the weight of passive indulgence and mindless binging. Yet the cruel irony remains: when we look back and examine what lingers after consuming such an astounding amount of content, we are often met with a mocking devil gesturing at us—a blank page and the quiet void of oblivion!</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="The-Cave"><a href="#The-Cave" class="headerlink" title="The Cave"></a>The Cave</h3><p>(2025.5.3) But still, we have social relations, and are thus constrained by societal expectations. We still have to strive for worldly things, to vie for power, to brandish our titles and our trophies for the world to see. Is it possible, to throw away all the forms of external confinements imposed by the society, the mind-forged manacles that serve as the source for our unhappiness? Unless we can crawl inside a cave, and remain solitary forever until the world forgets us, together with the dim shadows that we have cast. But that would be death and annihilation for the man floating amidst a sea of islands and the birth of a new land only lit by its own mind. (Note: But Blake managed to let his inner mind illuminate the world.)</p><h3 id="The-Ascent"><a href="#The-Ascent" class="headerlink" title="The Ascent"></a>The Ascent</h3><p>(2025.5.6) Dante intends to climb up the glorious mountain of felicity but is instead scared to death by the three beasts guarding the ascending path. Similarly, procrastination is born out of fear, doubt and the sense of being overwhelmed. It is the self-admitted defeat even before the battle begins. It is the poison tree growing from stagnant water, accumulating toxins around its roots, and preparing to release its paralytic effects upon the human mind that nurtures it with the tempting escapism rooted in conscious infirmity and unconscious despair. How should we, then, liberate ourselves from this abominable paralysis, these heavy chains of inertia? Step by step, as we reclaim our autonomy with glittering hope, unyielding courage, and an adamant will to power, even the direst situation may begin to change for the better. Perhaps, beneath the everlasting flux of things, there runs a golden stream of cause and effect that guides us towards our destination, the fragrant blossoming meadows along it patiently inviting us to tread upon.</p><h3 id="The-Fate"><a href="#The-Fate" class="headerlink" title="The Fate"></a>The Fate</h3><p>(2025.5.7) Fate, with her stately commands and veiled visage, comes upon our door and silently knocks. She is seeking the Sun inside every one of us, the Sun that can dispel all the lurking darkness and thaw all the biting frost, the Sun that can make even the most tedious days of Sisyphus seem joyous and worthwhile, the Sun that rises eternally inside and continues to illuminate everything outside. This is the process of soul-making, of finding your Sun.</p><h3 id="The-Finalite"><a href="#The-Finalite" class="headerlink" title="The Finalité"></a>The Finalité</h3><p>(2025.5.3) Words are uttered, and after that, they cannot stay; they slip away like a speeded snail, leaving only the faint echoes of vague sounds. Words, once written, have already began to live a posthumous existence. As for the answers, they can only be found after the finalité.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb3e658cb8da5c8e6665f.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Downfall&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Downfall&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Downfall&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Downfall&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;(2025.5.4) Every age has its own plight, and the relentless consumption of media is one of ours. In the vast expanse of cyberspace, many of us have succumbed to a peculiar kind of gluttony—a ceaseless craving perpetuated by the bombardment of video games, anime, provocative content, and endless streams of short videos. This insatiable beast, ever hungrier after feeding, has not only eaten away our time, but more importantly, our mind—our ability to concentrate is eroded, replaced by a constant pursuit of the new and the stimulating; the passage of time, once a steady flow, now feels disjointed and surreally fleeting; our experiences, once cohesively expanding throughout the day, have fragmented into foggy moments clouded by digital haze; creativity, the expression of the human spirit, lies dormant under the weight of passive indulgence and mindless binging. Yet the cruel irony remains: when we look back and examine what lingers after consuming such an astounding amount of content, we are often met with a mocking devil gesturing at us—a blank page and the quiet void of oblivion!&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Society" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Society/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Resentment</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/04/28/on-resentment/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/04/28/on-resentment/</id>
    <published>2025-04-27T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T12:11:04.308Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681c9f4e58cb8da5c8e62fbc.png"></p><p>Resentment refers to the bitter indignation at having been treated unfairly. By examining this definition, it is easy to identify the two indispensable components of this emotional state – “having been treated unfairly” as the external event that triggers such an emotion, and “bitter indignation” as the internal response towards such an event.</p><span id="more"></span><p>In order to dive into the complex and interlocking causal chain behind such a reaction, first, let us focus on the imagined root cause of this emotion, the said “culprit” who is out of our control. This silent burying of anger and bitterness originates in the belief that everyone, especially us, should be treated fairly. But, how do we define “fairness” in such a context? Due to the partial nature of subjectivity, we tend to subconsciously ascribe the attribute of fairness to many things that are simply <em>desirable</em> for us, especially when we have made an exertion to get them, or the undesirable outcome involves certain violation of rules in our opinion. When the ideal scenario fails to manifest itself in the real life, we think that we do not deserve to be treated so poorly. But the thing is, can this particular interpretation of fairness represent all different forms of fairness? If we dwell upon the fairness of God, or Nature, it might be another story altogether – everything inherently obeys the law of nature, including the people who give us an “unfair” jurisdiction. Our strive for fairness shares the same psychological root that motivates these people to treat us in a seemingly unfair way. Yes, maybe they are trying to deprive us of self-esteem and even happiness. But are they not doing it out of their own psychological deficiencies, such as incompetence, fear, or insecurity? Those who inflicts suffering suffer intensely, and the best defense is not to allow such negativity to eat away our felicity, so that the wrathful fire can only burn the stone-throwers.</p><p>Second, let’s focus on the relationship between the internal emotional state and the external event. Is resentment the necessary outcome of being treated unfairly? The answer is seemingly true because we are all culturally programmed to believe that is the case. When we were young, we learned from our parents or teachers that the feeling of bitterness and anger after being unjustly treated is perfectly justified, or rather, it is actually the only “normal” reaction of a living and breathing human being. But that does not make it as inevitable as the force of gravity which makes us stand on the ground, because instead of acting as a force of nature, it acts through cultural conditioning. Imagine, two group of people are from two distinct cultures. The first group are constantly told that everything happens to them represents the will of a divine being, and eventually everything will make sense through the interactions of a very complex web of interrelated events. And the second group are constantly reminded that bad things happen to them because they are not competent enough, or because other people want to harm them for whatever reason. It is easy to imagine the vast difference in attitudes and reactions when these two groups of people are put into the same situation. Suppose they <strong>think</strong> they are ****unfairly treated by the judge in a football match. The first group will try to reason out the underlying meaning and implications behind such a treatment, leading to more patient understanding before any rash actions, while the second group will tend to become instantly antagonistic towards the judge, dwelling upon their anger and bitterness, maybe eventually become so occupied by these negative thoughts that they decide to unleash a savage verbal attack towards the judge without sufficiently reflecting upon their own potential deficiencies.</p><p>Now that we have discussed: 1) our perception of being treated unfairly might originate in the varying definitions of fairness and the highly subjective nature of our experience; 2) the feeling of bitter anger is not the inevitable result of external events, but rather, it is established and reinforced by repetitive cultural conditioning which works in the subconscious level and becomes automatic in our emotional responses. Then, the key question becomes, how do we avoid being resentful after experiencing such events? First, being aware of the cultural conditioning involved in our emotional responses is the essential first step towards improvement. Instead of serving as the exercise of our free will and the fuel for our well-being, resentment is more likely to be the product of the unconscious following of the band-wagon, the “mutiny within”. Second, realize that our mental well-being is still within our grasp, and if after taking all the plausible actions, the injustice remains unchanged, then suspend the judgement of its effects might be more reasonable, because on one knows whether it will lead to bliss or bane amidst the complex web of events. By doing so, we choose to remain open before the unknown, recognize the interrelatedness of everything, and acknowledge that all is involved in the continuous creation of <em>Deus sive Natura.</em></p><p><em>Note: this piece of writing is an experiment of adopting Utilitarianism and Spinozist metaphysics to alleviate the pain brought by resentment, and does not necessarily reflect the author’s full take on this subject – if you are one of those artists, whose focus must be vastly different, leaning towards the creation of beauty based on experience and understanding, seeking to transform the grotesque into the beautiful instead of merely trying to comprehend the birth of resentment in the intellectual level, then this article can perhaps only serve as an interesting thought experiment, for your burden, your mission, your thorny paths of roses, lie elsewhere.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681c9f4e58cb8da5c8e62fbc.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resentment refers to the bitter indignation at having been treated unfairly. By examining this definition, it is easy to identify the two indispensable components of this emotional state – “having been treated unfairly” as the external event that triggers such an emotion, and “bitter indignation” as the internal response towards such an event.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Psychology" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Psychology/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Poetry Reading</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/03/10/on-poetry-reading/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/03/10/on-poetry-reading/</id>
    <published>2025-03-09T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:11:27.374Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca26058cb8da5c8e635cb.png"></p><blockquote><p><em>“When there is poetry,<br>it is Orpheus singing. He lightly comes and goes.”<br>                                                  - Rainer Maria Rilke</em></p></blockquote><p>Poetry reading is one of the most enriching of all social activities. And it is an activity uniquely human. Despite the myriads of ways a nightingale or a skylark sings to the fading night or the rising morn, they do not indulge in anything that could be called the chanting of poems, those sweetest songs of humanity that often “tell of saddest thought”.</p><span id="more"></span><p>The allure of poetry reading lies in its ability to unite and to enchant, to reconjure what is beautiful collectively. A group of people assemble around the table, like in an ancient Greek symposium. Together or one by one, they chant poems about death, love, war and peace, allowing the music of words to pierce the guarded wit and pass into the panting heart beneath. Poetry reading does not commence from a fixed point, and no one anticipates where the flow of verses might lead as it weaves and dances, ignites or simply glows. The foe of a captivating poetry reading is the individual who insists on deciphering every single line. Poetry reading is not about solving a complex puzzle; it is like diving into a lake, with an aim not to “immediately swim to the shore”, but to “luxuriate in the sensation of water”. There is no intellectual victory or defeat in poetry reading. In truth, the finest participants are those willing to embrace endless ambiguities and succumb to the musical flow of sounds. Just when people think they have grasped the essence of a stanza or made acquittance with a poem, the next rereading unfolds, adding a brand new layer of meaning and possibilities. They are ready to start anew.</p><p>Perhaps it is owing to my experiences in intimate bookshop gatherings that I find poetry readings possess a unique charm. The fellow attendees are not deeply entwined in each other’s personal narratives. Instead, they choose to completely immerse in the world of poetry, to give those mending hearts, unspoken fears, burning desires and hidden vulnerabilities a local habitation and a name. Together, they chant poems; together, they chant their souls. No more words are needed; silence can tend to the rest. This is the unutterable bliss of poetry reading.</p><p></br></br><br>附：小诗一首 —— 《门》</p><p>她静静地走向那扇门。<br>那扇孤寂的、长满青苔的铁的造物，<br>上面突兀地镌刻着“Amor Fati”。<br>于她而言，<br>那无疑是冰冷的，以至于封隔世界的存在。</p><p>第一次叩响。无言。<br>指节与金属相撞的声音，不断震荡在门的身躯里。<br>回环的、扩散的音波，却只被沉寂回应，<br>一如她被尘压在门后的记忆。</p><p>第二次叩响。微弱的、颤动的“啊”<br>扭动着如蛆虫从门后传来，<br>似哀鸣，似长叹，<br>似被黑夜升起的浓烟遮掩的呼吸。</p><p>第三次叩响。沉重的、斥责的“莫”<br>夹杂着拒绝与死的威严，<br>似警戒，似劝言，<br>似被晨雾包裹的一瞬的露珠。</p><p>第四次叩响。腾跃的、自由的“法”<br>直行着、坚决地穿透了钢铁，<br>似抚慰，似告诫，<br>似被正午的太阳许诺的追逐。</p><p>第五次叩响。终结的、延续的“啼”<br>回转着、围绕了全世界，<br>似轻语，似梦呓，<br>似被黄昏念想晕染的霞与月。</p><p>即将叩响的手指悬停。<br>门静伫依然。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca26058cb8da5c8e635cb.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When there is poetry,&lt;br&gt;it is Orpheus singing. He lightly comes and goes.”&lt;br&gt;                                                  - Rainer Maria Rilke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poetry reading is one of the most enriching of all social activities. And it is an activity uniquely human. Despite the myriads of ways a nightingale or a skylark sings to the fading night or the rising morn, they do not indulge in anything that could be called the chanting of poems, those sweetest songs of humanity that often “tell of saddest thought”.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Forgetfulness</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/23/on-forgetfulness/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/23/on-forgetfulness/</id>
    <published>2025-02-22T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:33:09.491Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681caa9558cb8da5c8e64fd3.png"></p><p>As human beings, we tend to forget things, sometimes rather quickly and against our will. We reach out our hands, often quite desperately, to grasp the precious moment as it slips away. We take photos, write notes, and try so hard to bore our eyes into the ephemeral nature of things.  </p><span id="more"></span><p>Forgetfulness explains and justifies so many seemingly bizarre behaviours of human beings that might never be comprehended or apprehended by gods or animals alike. It is deeply related to being mortal, experiencing this limited existence, which only lasts for a few thousand days and is no more.</p><p>Some say that it is not how things happen to us that really matters, but how we choose to perceive or experience them. As for the representations of things in our memory, maybe it is not how we actually experience them that matters, but how we choose to remember them, to commemorate them that really counts. We can bequeath the fleeting shadows of the shattered past with the most beautiful wreath of flowers; we can weave what was and what is into a carefully crafted personal anthology of subjective revaluation; we can contextualise and transform our unique history into a continuum of multiplying identities and expanding selves. Our memory, as it slowly fades away, can yet become so much more, with the glow of imagination and the flow of narration.</p><blockquote><p>“These were the pranks she played among the cities<br>Of mortal men, and what she did to Sprites<br>And Gods, entangling them in her sweet ditties<br>To do her will, and show their subtle sleights,<br>I will declare another time; for it is<br>A tale more fit for the weird winter nights<br>Than for these garish summer days, when we<br>Scarcely believe much more than we can see.”<sup>1</sup></p></blockquote><h2 id="References"><a href="#References" class="headerlink" title="References"></a>References</h2><p><sup>1</sup>Percy Shelley, <em>The Witch of Atlas</em>, Line 665.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681caa9558cb8da5c8e64fd3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As human beings, we tend to forget things, sometimes rather quickly and against our will. We reach out our hands, often quite desperately, to grasp the precious moment as it slips away. We take photos, write notes, and try so hard to bore our eyes into the ephemeral nature of things.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Be the Master of Technology</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/20/the-master-of-technology/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/20/the-master-of-technology/</id>
    <published>2025-02-19T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T12:56:27.137Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca8dc58cb8da5c8e6495e.png"></p><h3 id="Introduction"><a href="#Introduction" class="headerlink" title="Introduction"></a>Introduction</h3><p>In today’s world of booming technologies, we face a serious problem: how to effectively utilise technology so that we can become its master instead of its slave.</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="Looking-back"><a href="#Looking-back" class="headerlink" title="Looking back"></a>Looking back</h3><p>I believe many people have similar experiences: in a dark room, lying prostrate on the bed, scrolling the phone endlessly, not doing anything particularly, I am merely trying to extend the length of the day, of course, in vain. As time flies, I find this bad habit particularly pernicious, for it harms not only our eyes but also our brain, draining the energy originally prepared for a new day. Now, I have decided to change.</p><h3 id="Moving-forward"><a href="#Moving-forward" class="headerlink" title="Moving forward"></a>Moving forward</h3><p>To master technology instead of being mastered by it, we need to pay attention to everyday details, the so-called “minute particulars”, to quote William Blake’s words, for there lies the secrets of habit formation.</p><p>For me, desktop OS (Windows&#x2F;MacOS&#x2F;Linux) means productivity, while Android&#x2F;iOS implies consumption, mainly because of the differences in terms of interaction mode and application ecosystem. On a computer, one can simply do more things, and the multitasking capacity is also considerably higher than that of a phone; one is more inclined to use keyboard and trackpad&#x2F;mouse, which makes the act of using the device more consciously done than scrolling and tapping almost unconsciously on a phone.</p><p>Next comes the question - what kinds of computers then? To adapt to various scenarios, the device should be versatile and light, elegantly designed and enjoyable to use; ideally, it should be both a computer and a mobile device, so that most scenarios that require a touchscreen can also be covered. After applying all these filters, the answer seems rather obvious to me -  Microsoft Surface Pro, which is both a computer and a tablet, with a detachable keyboard cover and an attachable digital pen, making it one of the most versatile devices available on the market. Most games are not suitable for running on this device, which can be a good thing for productivity.</p><h3 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h3><p>Of course, choosing the appropriate device is just the beginning; what comes next may be more important - use the device to experience and to create more beautiful and meaningful things.</p><p>I desire to go back to the olden ways of interacting with virtual worlds - books and a computer.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca8dc58cb8da5c8e6495e.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Introduction&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In today’s world of booming technologies, we face a serious problem: how to effectively utilise technology so that we can become its master instead of its slave.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Technology" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Technology/"/>
    
    <category term="Lifestyle" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Lifestyle/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>诗四首：春交响</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/01/18/four-poems-spring/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/01/18/four-poems-spring/</id>
    <published>2025-01-17T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43ef0d0e0a243d4fc1be1.jpg"></p><h3 id="一、骨笛"><a href="#一、骨笛" class="headerlink" title="一、骨笛"></a>一、骨笛</h3><center>欢快与忧伤在心中流淌，<p>这远古悠扬的乐音，来自何方？</p></br><p>当人类生的呼吸贯通你死的鸣腔，</p><p>每一丝破裂的纹路，都盈满空气的激荡。</p><span id="more"></span></br><p>于是我听到，那静谧的死亡，仍在生长。</p><p>你倔强的骨节，决意奏出灵魂的鸣响。</p></br><p>几百年过去，歇落的只是反抗的奢望，</p><p>顺应了自然的构想，</p><p>此刻的你，不也仍在飞翔，仍在歌唱？</p></br><h3 id="二、春日繁花"><a href="#二、春日繁花" class="headerlink" title="二、春日繁花"></a>二、春日繁花</h3><p>从混沌的沼泽扯出金色的丝线，</p><p>将寄居此处溺亡的泥泞，</p><p>都凝成编织春日繁花的梦境。</p></br><h3 id="三、命运"><a href="#三、命运" class="headerlink" title="三、命运"></a>三、命运</h3><p>在旷野中寻找命运</p><p>那摇晃的恍如永恒的一刹。</p></br><p>Amor Fati… Amor Fati…</p><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a45fb0d0e0a243d4fc2a89.webp" alt="img"></p></br><h3 id="四、愚神的春日"><a href="#四、愚神的春日" class="headerlink" title="四、愚神的春日"></a>四、愚神的春日</h3><p>我于愚神的春日醒来，</p><p>四方已然落花一片，流水无言。</p><p>远去的幻影朦胧如烟，</p><p>晕散在樱染的暮帘。</p></br><p>什么可以抓得住？</p><p>怎样才能不忘却？</p><p>这独属我的小房间。</p><p>在目送过无数流连的眼，</p><p>终于还是，</p><p>唯有这春日相伴。</center></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43ef0d0e0a243d4fc1be1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;一、骨笛&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#一、骨笛&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;一、骨笛&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;一、骨笛&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;欢快与忧伤在心中流淌，

&lt;p&gt;这远古悠扬的乐音，来自何方？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当人类生的呼吸贯通你死的鸣腔，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每一丝破裂的纹路，都盈满空气的激荡。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="诗歌" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E8%AF%97%E6%AD%8C/"/>
    
    <category term="文学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E6%96%87%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="写作" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%86%99%E4%BD%9C/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Six Poems - Dreamy Nights</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2024/06/30/six-poems-dreamy-nights/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2024/06/30/six-poems-dreamy-nights/</id>
    <published>2024-06-29T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.556Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43d5fd0e0a243d4fc1b7d.jpg"></p><h3 id="I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep"><a href="#I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep" class="headerlink" title="I. The Bells of Black Sheep"></a>I. The Bells of Black Sheep</h3><center><p>Dark clouds congregate across the sky</p><p>Of crystal blue, where a fragile butterfly</p><p>Attempts to soar high with golden wings</p><p>For vain hope, swirling and flitting in the wind.</p><span id="more"></span></br><p>Above the clouds twenty sheep solemnly stand,</p><p>Proud their mien, regal even, like the ministers</p><p>Heralding demise, those from that mysterious land</p><p>Of decay and despair, tolling the bells of disaster.</p><p>The sound is slow and heavy, pulsating like heartbeats</p><p>Which blindly run through the threads of creation</p><p>And end with a knit of mighty necessity, leaving</p><p>Visages pale, wings broken and hearts drown in emotion.</p></br><p>The faerie butterfly, beholding the upcoming abyss,</p><p>Calmly accepts her destiny, and begins to dream</p><p>The sweetest dream she could ever conceive,</p><p>A dream of blooming flowers dancing,</p><p>Of music flowing, infants smiling,</p><p>Of moonlight shining, suns rising,</p><p>Of Garden of Eden endowed with original beauty,</p><p>Everything joyfully living.</p></br><p>Fear dissipates in the reverie of hope,</p><p>And bells seem to cease for its sake, idling</p><p>Away the hours of their noonday, considering</p><p>The possibility of a starlit night, though fleeting,</p><p>With the most astonishing display</p><p>Of butterfly dance, which can illuminate</p><p>Even the darkest dale in the universe.</p></br><p>The flood of light effuses from the sky.</p></br><h3 id="II-A-Bee’s-Escapism"><a href="#II-A-Bee’s-Escapism" class="headerlink" title="II. A Bee’s Escapism"></a>II. A Bee’s Escapism</h3><p>Here comes a golden bee, </p><p>Fleeing from its drenchèd flight, </p><p>Buzzing round a pile of dung.</p></br><p>O, fair dweller of sweet fragrance, </p><p>When thy wings to heaviness sink, </p><p>Thou dost choose a jail of stink, </p><p>To escape the wearied voyage</p></br><p>In a humid day</p><p>Of battering rain.</p></br><h3 id="III-Nightsong"><a href="#III-Nightsong" class="headerlink" title="III. Nightsong"></a>III. Nightsong</h3><p>The day departs. Two mournful shadows rise</p><p>With voices vain and gloomy, blowing death.</p><p>Their bones decay, their heavy steps surmise</p><p>The dreary fears that men dare not confess.</p><p>Until a lance of light is thrown through night,</p><p>Diffusing odours sweet as blooming rose,</p><p>Then they dissolve like morning dew in flight</p><p>Of dread, and find in tombs eterne repose.</p><p>The chaste and gentle moon of Love ascends</p><p>In perfect glory, shining dizzy beams</p><p>On those resentful phantoms’ timely ends,</p><p>Dispersing haunting dreams with silver gleams.</p><p>The spinning wheel of life then rolls apace,</p><p>Across the land serene, in endless grace.</p></br><h3 id="IV-Mystical-Pageantry"><a href="#IV-Mystical-Pageantry" class="headerlink" title="IV. Mystical Pageantry"></a>IV. Mystical Pageantry</h3><p>Many a bird is singing in the forest</p><p>Of reverie and mirth, with various music</p><p>Floating through the decaying trees deformed</p><p>By endless battering of dragging years.</p></br><p>Pageants of Queens and Kings bizzarely march</p><p>With solemn precision and knightly strength</p><p>Penetrating the trembling air of morning</p><p>And piercing through the mystery of summer.</p></br><h3 id="V-Blackbird"><a href="#V-Blackbird" class="headerlink" title="V. Blackbird"></a>V. Blackbird</h3><p>A blackbird hops along the street, her steps</p><p>Tender and light, her eyes amass the breath</p><p>Of gentle purple dawn and crimson sun</p><p>Of June, the loving prophecy of life,</p><p>Delicate forms of nature’s patient art.</p></br><p>O, thou embassador of Endless Rhymes!</p><p>Thy song transcends the petty scope of minds</p><p>And flies across the slow and crawling Time,</p><p>Towards the region strange, unknown, sublime,</p><p>A heart renewed, a forehead divine!</p></br><h3 id="VI-Crescendo"><a href="#VI-Crescendo" class="headerlink" title="VI. Crescendo"></a>VI. Crescendo</h3><p>O, Gentle Soul,</p><p>Gently breathing sorrow,</p></br><p>Sighing like a Deluge foretold</p><p>By the Lightening fierce and bold</p><p>Bursting through the purple Nights of Old</p></br><p>Before the Crescent Moon wore her garments cold.</p></br></center>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43d5fd0e0a243d4fc1b7d.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;I. The Bells of Black Sheep&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I. The Bells of Black Sheep&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark clouds congregate across the sky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of crystal blue, where a fragile butterfly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attempts to soar high with golden wings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For vain hope, swirling and flitting in the wind.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
    <category term="Art" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Art/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Governmental Patronage in the Development of the Arts</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2024/02/10/on-governmental-patronage-for-the-development-of-arts/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2024/02/10/on-governmental-patronage-for-the-development-of-arts/</id>
    <published>2024-02-09T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:54:00.630Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb10458cb8da5c8e66054.png"></p><p>A vagabond wanders alone through the streets, clutching a drawing board in his hand, still chasing after the elusive God of Art with eyes eager to discover beauty. He is, undeniably, a drifter in the age of materialism—a living embodiment of the “poor artist” archetype, one often dismissed as an outcast, yet standing as an unyielding testament to creative perseverance. This image may evoke heartache and dismay, yet it is also the reality that many artists in modern society face, navigating an existence where passion must battle pragmatism. However, with government support, artists can sustain their craft, and their livelihoods may be preserved. In my view, such an act is not merely generous—it is an affirmation of the intrinsic value of artistic expression in human civilization.</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="The-Symbolic-Relationship-Between-Art-and-Civilization"><a href="#The-Symbolic-Relationship-Between-Art-and-Civilization" class="headerlink" title="The Symbolic Relationship Between Art and Civilization"></a>The Symbolic Relationship Between Art and Civilization</h3><p>The skepticism surrounding government assistance for artists stems largely from a utilitarian approach to economics—one that prioritizes industrial advancement and scientific progress above cultural investment. Opponents argue that national wealth should be directed toward infrastructure, technology, and scientific discovery, which, in their view, are the true engines of modern progress. Yet, history tells a different tale—one that reminds us that the progress of humanity is never solely measured by material wealth or technological milestones, but also by the intangible brilliance of creativity and culture.</p><p>The Renaissance offers one of history’s most compelling counterexamples. Without the House of Medici generously funding talented yet struggling artists, the world may never have known the genius of Leonardo da Vinci, the architectural grandeur of Gothic cathedrals, or the poetic depth of Botticelli’s “Primavera.” Their patronage did more than sustain the livelihoods of painters and sculptors—it ignited a cultural revolution, one that reshaped philosophy, literature, and political thought. Florence, through its investment in the arts, became a beacon of intellectual and artistic excellence, a city remembered through the ages not merely for its economic prosperity but for its contributions to human expression and ingenuity.</p><h3 id="Economic-and-Social-Implications"><a href="#Economic-and-Social-Implications" class="headerlink" title="Economic and Social Implications"></a>Economic and Social Implications</h3><p>Beyond historical precedent, contemporary society continues to thrive on artistic innovation. While opponents may argue that the arts do not yield immediate financial returns, the cultural industry proves otherwise. Cities known for their artistic vibrancy—Paris, Florence, Beijing—are not just cultural landmarks but thriving economic hubs, drawing millions of tourists, investors, and scholars each year. The presence of renowned artists elevates a city’s status, transforming it into a space of both economic and intellectual exchange.</p><p>Furthermore, supporting artists is not merely an economic strategy; it is an act of human solidarity. Given the unpredictable nature of creative work, many artists struggle at the outset of their careers, making financial assistance not only beneficial but, at times, essential. Often, all an artistic genius needs is a fertile space to grow. Without such encouragement, countless potential masterpieces may remain unrealized, lost to history due to the crushing weight of financial instability.</p><h3 id="The-Transformative-Power-of-Art"><a href="#The-Transformative-Power-of-Art" class="headerlink" title="The Transformative Power of Art"></a>The Transformative Power of Art</h3><p>Art is more than an aesthetic endeavor—it shapes ideology, inspires revolutions, and expands the boundaries of human consciousness. Literature, film, music, and visual arts all serve as conduits through which societies explore identity, challenge norms, and foster unity. A nation that invests in its artists is not merely subsidizing individuals; it is cultivating visionaries who will shape the collective imagination of generations to come.</p><p>Consider the transformative power of the Harlem Renaissance, in which Black artists, writers, and musicians redefined cultural narratives and reshaped dialogues on race and identity. Consider the impact of Picasso’s “Guernica,” a painting that transcended canvas to become a political statement against war. Consider the literary power of James Joyce or Gabriel García Márquez—authors whose works provided entire nations with voices that resonated beyond borders. Without support, many of these figures may never have reached their potential. And without artistic expression, societies risk stagnation—trapped in an existence devoid of reflection, storytelling, or emotional depth.</p><h3 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h3><p>Government support for artists is not merely an act of generosity—it is an investment in the intellectual, emotional, and cultural growth of a nation. It is a commitment to the idea that progress is not merely technological or economic, but also creative and philosophical. It ensures that future generations inherit a legacy rich not only in scientific discovery but in artistic brilliance—the paintings, literature, music, and architecture that shape human history as profoundly as any invention.</p><p>Florence did not ascend to greatness through commerce alone, nor did Paris earn its reputation solely through industrial success. They flourished because they believed in art, nurtured it, and let it transform their cities into spaces of wonder and thought. Thus, supporting the arts is not just worthwhile—it is necessary.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb10458cb8da5c8e66054.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vagabond wanders alone through the streets, clutching a drawing board in his hand, still chasing after the elusive God of Art with eyes eager to discover beauty. He is, undeniably, a drifter in the age of materialism—a living embodiment of the “poor artist” archetype, one often dismissed as an outcast, yet standing as an unyielding testament to creative perseverance. This image may evoke heartache and dismay, yet it is also the reality that many artists in modern society face, navigating an existence where passion must battle pragmatism. However, with government support, artists can sustain their craft, and their livelihoods may be preserved. In my view, such an act is not merely generous—it is an affirmation of the intrinsic value of artistic expression in human civilization.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Arts" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Arts/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>论「混沌」</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/08/24/on-chaos/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/08/24/on-chaos/</id>
    <published>2023-08-23T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.552Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43cb7d0e0a243d4fc1b3c.jpg"></p><p>大地颤动着，似乎要吞噬伫立其上的一切：高耸的楼台，抑或青翠的密林，酣然的沉睡，抑或迷途的心。一切都被某种不可抗拒的力量禁锢，拉入一种更原始、更未经分化的状态。这是多元现象世界的塌落，是于虚无中走向统一的深渊。『混沌』是人类赋予它的名字。</p><span id="more"></span><p>在各地的神话与符号象征之中，随处可见『混沌』的踪迹。从奥维德变形记中所描绘的世界伊始，“自然的面庞在何处都别无二致，只是未经分割的无生命之物，却又潜藏着无数未来的种子与互相争斗的元素力”；到弥尔顿失乐园中撒旦所跌落的境界之地，“是天之外的冥荒与无尽的暗夜，沸腾的湖面上升腾起黑色火焰，灼烧着这片被迷失笼罩的无光之地”，『混沌』在任何时代，似乎都牵动着人们想象力中更加隐晦和神秘的部分，又好像在解释着一些不可言说的终极。在一些人眼里，『混沌』是沉重的命运，是对个体存在的否定，是崩坏的终极；在另一些人眼里，『混沌』是原初的希冀，是创造的前奏，是最后的归一。</p><p>但在各种对于『混沌』的想象与解释中，若能抽出一根丝线尝试将它们串联到一起，那大概会是『一元』，只不过这里的一元，潜藏着太多未知与黑暗、矛盾与野蛮，不同于另一极的秩序世界所注强调的灵与智能的统一，这里更多强调的则是形与物质的未分化。然而对于作为初状态的『混沌』而言，这样被混乱裹挟的空间，或者说连空间都不足以称得存在的状态，却同时也是孕育创造的地方。正因为这层虚空，一切可能性都有了潜在的居所，一切妄为的自由都被保证，一切崭新的开始都被承认，这层『无』是之后无数『有』的开端，是一颗包含了无限的种子，是所有故事最初的摇篮。而意义，也就必然从这虚无之中降生，正如诗句从潜意识的深渊奔涌而出一样，带着所有可能的光与热，美与希望，流向这世界。</p><p>而对于末状态的『混沌』而言，情况则看起来悲观得多，作为一切的湮灭，那意味着尘归尘，或者归于更加不可被辨别的物质，意味着发散到未知的时间与空间，意味着死亡。而这，又是否真的是最后的终极？人类或许穷尽无数个世纪都无法确定这个问题的答案。然而，我们却隐隐约约地感受到，在那之后的混沌中，仍会有如同之前一般互相争斗的元素，仍有着无数关于未来的种子与生命的可能，有着未实现的新的开端。也许，从古代流传下来的 Ouroboros（衔尾蛇）的形象就是于『混沌』之中走来，遍历了无尽的历史、现在与未来之后，归于混沌的沉寂，又开始混沌的新生，循环往复，不断轮回，如同旋转的无限，将自己的存在映射于宇宙的意识之上。</p><p>而『混沌』，也会凭着这旋转，这轮回，伴随着旧的毁灭与新的降生，完成它的一次又一次舞蹈吧。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43cb7d0e0a243d4fc1b3c.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大地颤动着，似乎要吞噬伫立其上的一切：高耸的楼台，抑或青翠的密林，酣然的沉睡，抑或迷途的心。一切都被某种不可抗拒的力量禁锢，拉入一种更原始、更未经分化的状态。这是多元现象世界的塌落，是于虚无中走向统一的深渊。『混沌』是人类赋予它的名字。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="哲学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%93%B2%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="随笔" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E7%AC%94/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>结合荣格认知功能对心理受困状态的思考</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/04/21/the-psychological-state-of-being-trapped%20copy/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/04/21/the-psychological-state-of-being-trapped%20copy/</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43c23d0e0a243d4fc1b2e.webp"></p><h4 id="关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应"><a href="#关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应" class="headerlink" title="关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应"></a>关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应</h4><h4 id="以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论"><a href="#以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论" class="headerlink" title="以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论"></a>以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论</h4><p>人居于“受困”的处境，就好像于柏拉图的山洞寓言中凝视烛灯投影，将其奉为「真实」全部之人，只能在黑暗中摸索着洞穴的岩壁兜兜转转，而忘记了一个更广的世界的可能。</p><span id="more"></span><p>在这时，最鼓舞人心的词大概会是“超越”（transcendence），也即那第一个决定走出洞穴去拥抱阳光与更广阔天空的人所到达的境界。这里的“超越”，不单单是指对于当下所处或者基于过去所拟造的境遇的超越，同时也是对于“自我”（ego consciousness）的超越与扩张，是一次属于过去自己的小小死亡，也是一次属于活在当下与未来无数可能性中自己的崭新降生。而对于 INFP 而言，由于狭义的 Si 所聚焦的「过去经验」与 Fi 所提供的「内在价值判断与构筑」能力的相互作用影响（此处狭义的 Si 是指取了 Si 的来源之一，也即更为「个人」的来源，根据 Carl Jung 在 Psychological Types 中所定义的 Si —— “subjective perceptions which orientate his consciousness in accordance with an archaic reality”，Si 的来源至少可以大致分为两种 —— 个人的与人类的，其中基于人类过去所构筑的内在感知提供的视角是更为「原型」的一种认知世界的方式），有时会因为过去经历的一些造成不良心理效应的事件而产生一种“受困感”（虽然很显然，这种来源的“受困感”通行于全人类，但 Fi-Si 的作用确实在一定程度上会导致相对更频繁地触发）。</p><ul><li><p>Fi 的发展与丰富：这一点的本质其实是培养内源性信心与尊严 ，也因此具有了一定的「存在主义」属性。「意义」本身最终不能也不可能由任何外部机构或个人强加给我们，而是要由我们自己去发现并定义。在认识到我们的生活本身就充满了无限与「意义」相关的可能性，并有意识地开始与真善美等能够滋养心灵的价值共鸣的时候，个人的存在本身就成了信心与自尊的强大源泉，此时的「个人」，已经超越了外界的各种评价体系，而是以一种“我美好地存在于世界，这本身即是很高的价值”的语境面对生活，从而获得源源不断的内在信念支持。</p></li><li><p>Si 语义的扩张：根据上面注解中提出的 Carl Jung 对于 Si 的定义以及其大致的两种来源可知，除了个人过去的经历之外，Si 还可以来源于「人类的过去」，此处的过去不只局限于狭义的真实历史，而是人类过去时代所创作的所有诗歌、戏剧、音乐、哲学以及各种各样的关于生活的痕迹的总和。通过有意识地对「人类的过去」进行探索与理解，我们得以更加广泛又更加细密地了解人性本身，与此同时也超越了只有「自我的过去」的狭隘语境，从而以一种崭新的视角重新认知周围的一切。在「人类的过去」里，往往包含了一种更为宏大的叙事，如但丁从地狱到天堂的旅行，柯勒律治在勃朗峰所感受到的神明，在这些叙述之中，我们得以找到一种更具滋养性质的 Si 来源，与此同时，也得以带着崭新的视角重新审视个人过去的某些经历，从而将与 Si 相关的「内在对话」转换 ，让 Fi-Si 的效应更具有扩张属性。</p></li><li><p>Ne 与外界环境：Ne 作为 INFP 的第二功能，与外部世界直接相连，其本身就具有一定的超越性质。当我们漫步于自然之境，感受绿叶在风中的微微震颤，仰望头顶轻如薄梦缓缓飘浮的白云，听到欢愉无比好似倾泻灵魂的鸟鸣，并用 Ne 将这一切与我们的存在串联在一起，就会发现，万物本身，就是相互联系的。没有人，或者说，没有任何事物孤独地存在于这个世界，所有的存在都相互勾连影响，构成了一张无比庞大的意义网。而将这外部的一切于内心世界相互联结起来的我们，此时的心，不也正随着微风、白云与飞鸟一起，自由地漂游于这世间吗。</p></li><li><p>Te 与暂时性优化：Te 作为 INFP 的第四功能，发动起来并不如前三种功能容易，但是 Te 在一定程度确实可以在更为现实的角度让我们走出困境。比如每日进行一定规律性的室外运动，以及学会充满效率地完成想要完成的工作，都是不错的暂时性优化方法。</p></li></ul><p>以上片段从四种认知功能 Fi &#x2F; Ne &#x2F; Si &#x2F; Te 的角度分别探讨了走出“受困感”的可能，通过一些语义的转换与有意识的功能调用，我们得以将原本看似的“缺点”转换为优势，从而拥抱一个更为圆满的自己。其实，作为一个 INFP 来说，最重要的，也许还是一颗愿意不断认识自我并超越自我的心，以及对世间美好之物的相信与热爱吧。</p><blockquote><p>后记：在表面上看，本文进行的论述也许只是在荣格八维框架之内进行的分析，但考虑到人类特定心理状态的共同性质，以及荣格认知功能划分的局限性，以上分析则可以看作是借助流行文化而进行的人类心理的普遍论述。作为行走于世间、活生生的人类，而非某种被抽象范畴所定义的存在，我们应该也必将高于诸如认知功能此类纯粹理论的框架。所以，在借助梯子攀登上天台之后，就请用涌动着生命与自由的眼与心，去观测自我与这个世界吧，相信在那个时候，“解放”会变得离我们更近一步。</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43c23d0e0a243d4fc1b2e.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;人居于“受困”的处境，就好像于柏拉图的山洞寓言中凝视烛灯投影，将其奉为「真实」全部之人，只能在黑暗中摸索着洞穴的岩壁兜兜转转，而忘记了一个更广的世界的可能。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="哲学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%93%B2%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="随笔" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E7%AC%94/"/>
    
    <category term="心理学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%BF%83%E7%90%86%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Juvenalian &amp; Horatian Satire</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/05/juvenalian-horatian/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/05/juvenalian-horatian/</id>
    <published>2023-02-04T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4363bd0e0a243d4fc1a90.webp"></p><p>It is quite interesting to think about the motivations of Juvenalian satirists. The famous declaration made by Jonathan Swift, “to vex the world”, instead of being born from the simply attributed “cynicism” or “misanthropy”, ironically enough, actually originates from the innate belief in the possibilities of improvements in human society and the essential goodness of human nature. If one is merely cynical, it would make no sense at all for such fierce moral indignation, instead, one would simply shrug indifferently and walk away, which is exactly opposite to the vehement acts of a Juvenalian satirist, who is a true vindicator of social justice and liberty. Juvenalian satire is like the rallying cry of ancient prophets, full of energy and determination.</p><span id="more"></span><p>However, in my personal opinion, the employment of good humour is important as well, which can be considered one of the characteristics of Horatian satire, like the tone adopted in the mock-heroic narrative poem The Rape of the Lock written by Alexander Pope, for the “serious” pathway towards transcendence is spiritual enlightenment while the “unserious” one is light-hearted laughter; both have the power to dissolve the narrow confinement established by ego consciousness and lead us towards a more elevated and broadened view of reality.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4363bd0e0a243d4fc1a90.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is quite interesting to think about the motivations of Juvenalian satirists. The famous declaration made by Jonathan Swift, “to vex the world”, instead of being born from the simply attributed “cynicism” or “misanthropy”, ironically enough, actually originates from the innate belief in the possibilities of improvements in human society and the essential goodness of human nature. If one is merely cynical, it would make no sense at all for such fierce moral indignation, instead, one would simply shrug indifferently and walk away, which is exactly opposite to the vehement acts of a Juvenalian satirist, who is a true vindicator of social justice and liberty. Juvenalian satire is like the rallying cry of ancient prophets, full of energy and determination.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>论「自我」</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/02/on-self/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/02/on-self/</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.554Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43581d0e0a243d4fc1a69.jpg"></p><p>有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是月光洒不进的密林里幻化幽灵的追逐，是被其所困的牛犊下定决心找到答案的迷途，是元素精灵在毫无止息变化万千的暴风雨中的狂舞；有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是攀登出地狱的磐岩与烈焰之后重新瞩目的灿灿星辰，是在苦难之海漂泊良久的水手得以停歇的翠绿岛屿，是所不能及的无底深渊，也是一直在延展的遥遥远方。</p><span id="more"></span><p>「自我」难以被任何人类范畴严肃定义的原因之一是，它永远都在进化。这首与周围的世界万物一起谱写的名为「创造」的协奏曲，就像与一层又一层海浪相拥的细沙，留下了拥有无限复杂度的纹路。当我们在不断前行的路上，不再被「抽象」投射的阴影迷惑，并勇敢地摘下因为各种原因戴上的假面，其本质就会在「体验」中逐渐显现，这即是于存在与时间中磨洗并超越“我思故我在”所筑螺旋的 Dasein，即是对自中一切与其所视之物都表示爱与接纳的 Amor Fati，也即「自我」的超越。</p><p>如果我们仍能忆起孩童时的体验，大概会意识到，在那时，宇宙中的所有存在仿佛也都存在于「我」之中，但又拥有着他们各自恒久而闪烁的光芒，吸引着一颗小小的心不断去了解，去寻找，去发现。然而，随着时间的流逝与世事的变幻，那颗心仿佛也终于蒙上了「习惯」的尘，一切都变得熟悉而又无聊，甚至可憎。好在这些，终究也只不过是心的映像，是我们为自己所加的「叙述」，而不一定是事物的「真相」。所以，掀开那将「自我」与「世界」隔离的面纱，去拥抱，这一切吧。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43581d0e0a243d4fc1a69.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是月光洒不进的密林里幻化幽灵的追逐，是被其所困的牛犊下定决心找到答案的迷途，是元素精灵在毫无止息变化万千的暴风雨中的狂舞；有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是攀登出地狱的磐岩与烈焰之后重新瞩目的灿灿星辰，是在苦难之海漂泊良久的水手得以停歇的翠绿岛屿，是所不能及的无底深渊，也是一直在延展的遥遥远方。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="哲学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%93%B2%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="随笔" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E7%AC%94/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Dorian Gray</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/12/01/dorian-gray/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/12/01/dorian-gray/</id>
    <published>2022-11-30T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/6388b73d16f2c2beb19dec11.jpg"></p><p><em>The Picture of Dorian Gray</em> is a philosophical novel written by the Irish writer Oscar Wilde. It tells us that hedonism and amoral actions will eventually lead the tempted to decay and death without ever trying to tell it. Oscar Wilde wrote it without any moralistic intention due to his belief in aestheticism, which claims art itself is useless thus without any social implication. Bearing this philosophy of art in mind, this work destines to be a book of open interpretations, a book elevated or deprecated by the view lens adopted by different people, a world full of possibilities, just like every other great novel ever written.</p><span id="more"></span><p>The story revolves around a portrait of Dorian Gray painted by Basil, an artist infatuated with Dorian’s beauty. Through Basil, Dorian meets Lord Henry Wotton and is deeply impressed by the hedonistic worldview adopted by the aristocrats. After this encounter, the meaning of life is thrown into the dark abyss of void and non-existence; Dorian’s only occupation becomes the pursuit of sensual pleasure and outward beauty. But here comes the problem - beauty will eventually decay. So Dorian decides that he will give up his soul and make a deal with the devil, just like Doctor Faust. Because of this evil contract, the portrait, rather than Dorian, will age and fade. The wish is granted and Dorian pursues a life of amoral experiences while staying young and beautiful. At the same time, his portrait ages and records every sin that Dorian has committed, a discordant collection of crimes and decadence.</p><p>Apart from the novel proper, its preface is already a masterpiece by itself. In the preface, Oscar Wilde claims that “to reveal art and conceal artist is art’s aim” and “the highest as the lowest form of criticism is a mode of autobiography”, which profoundly points out the mimetic and reflective nature of literature and literary criticism. In Shakespeare’s plays, it is extremely hard to know what kind of person Shakespeare is; his religious, political, and even philosophical views remain vague for modern readers, shrouded in mystery. Because every character portraited by the bard lives his own life, in the glorious world of imagination; they reflect certain traits of humanity, and ultimately become humanity itself, concealing the artist in the this process. And when we are trying to read a book, we are actually looking into a dynamic mirror which tells more about us than about the book or the author. That is exactly why Wilde connects criticism and autobiography in such an intimate way. This specific view of art and literary criticism is essential to the understanding of the novel, for it liberates us from mindlessly condemning it as a book of decadence and decay merely because it tells a story of hedonism. By choosing to be free, we can delve deeper into its complex themes and probe towards the innermost part of our own soul.</p><p>In my opinion, this life in pursuit of sensual pleasure led by Dorian, is actually not a joyful life at all. Because it is totally devoid of meaning and only reveals life’s emptiness and absurdity in the end, when all the fleeting passion finally dies away. Lasting happiness, ironically enough, is not actually something we can consciously chase after, but the by-product of some other human conducts. It is not because the expectation of joy that makes us fall in love but because we decide to love and as a result end up embracing the experience of ecstasy. Our life is a hero’s journey, a lover’s journey, a journey which requires efforts and devotion, not some trivial funny games with the only intention of instant gratification. Just like Nietzsche said, “he who knows a why can bear any how”, human beings naturally crave for meaning, that is what makes us “human becoming” because once guided by the intricate and complex web of meaning, we are destined to embark upon so many fabulous journeys full of perils and presents; we can finally climb up the mountain of eternal joy. This is the happiness of maturity, of becoming truly who we can become in the end.</p><p>“All art is quite useless”, Oscar Wilde concludes his preface with this sentence. But is that really so? By reflecting upon the surface and symbol of art at the same time, by looking into the mirror with our deepest heart’s core, we begin to discern the great use of art, which might be unique to everyone’s experience and perhaps can never be made universal, but it will always guide us in the fierce storms and dark nights. “The artist is the creator of beautiful things”, and we, as readers, should be artists as well.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/6388b73d16f2c2beb19dec11.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; is a philosophical novel written by the Irish writer Oscar Wilde. It tells us that hedonism and amoral actions will eventually lead the tempted to decay and death without ever trying to tell it. Oscar Wilde wrote it without any moralistic intention due to his belief in aestheticism, which claims art itself is useless thus without any social implication. Bearing this philosophy of art in mind, this work destines to be a book of open interpretations, a book elevated or deprecated by the view lens adopted by different people, a world full of possibilities, just like every other great novel ever written.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Book Reviews" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Book-Reviews/"/>
    
    <category term="Literary Criticism" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literary-Criticism/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Book of Thel</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/28/the-book-of-thel/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/28/the-book-of-thel/</id>
    <published>2022-11-27T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4313bd0e0a243d4fc1919.jpg"></p><p><em>The Book of Thel</em> is one of the prophetic illuminated books written by William Blake, a great British poet, painter and visionary born in the 18th Century. Crafted after <em>The Song of Innocence</em>, this allegorical poem is closely related to the loss of innocence, perhaps also indicating the creation of <em>The Song of Experience</em> in the following years.</p><span id="more"></span><p>The poem begins with Thel, the youngest daughter of Mne Seraphim, who separates herself and goes to the river. There, Thel laments about the transience of mortal life and the inevitability of death. The Lily of the valley, upon hearing her words, replies that even as weak and insignificant as she can be blessed by the almighty God and everything that lives should rejoice instead of complaining. Thel responds by listing the virtues of the Lily and compares herself to a cloud, dying without leaving a trace. So she continues to ask a little cloud about mutability. The cloud explains that transience is born out of Love and death is beautiful, for it means the transformation into a more romantic and unified way of existence. Thel responds with a lamentation upon her uselessness, fearing her only use after death will be feeding worms. The cloud says it is also a great use because it emphasizes the interconnectedness of all forms of life. Then, the cloud asks a worm to come to Thel, but the worm cannot speak, it only cries like a feeble infant. Soon after, a clod of clay joins them and claims even the worm is still loved by the divine. Invited by the clod of clay, Thel agrees to come to the clay’s home, where the couches of the dead and the fibrous roots intertwine. Wandering through this land of sorrow and tears, she finally comes to her own grave, where she is asked by a mysterious voice about the perception of the five senses. Upon hearing the possible woe perceived by these sensory organs, Thel runs back to the vale with a shriek.</p><p>In <em>The Book of Thel</em>, The Vales of Har are depicted as a paradisal place which resembles the Garden of Eden. Thel wishes to enter the world of experience and leave the innocent paradise behind. However, once Thel enters the world of experience, her heart is filled with terror upon the thought of mortality and the futility of human conducts considering the final demise is inevitable. But at the same time, her escape from all these possible pain and sorrow also leads to the inability to perceive all the beautiful things in the mortal life. Sometimes, it is exactly the transient nature of things that makes them more precious, like sweet music floating in the air and gradually dying away. In other words, Thel’s fear towards growing up is what keeps her from actually living. When she flees from the world of experience, she is also fleeing from the fullness of life itself. Innocence should take on a more elevated meaning, one found through suffering, through fire and frost, that Thel can never reach as long as she is gripped by the fear of opening herself up to risk. In order to truly become mature, one must face all these fabulous perils scattered along the journey. Our life is meant to be a hero’s journey, maybe unlike that of Achilles and Odysseus, but still possesses its own form of heroism. We need to slay the evil fire-breathing dragons, jump into the deep den of despair and rise up from the ruin of life all over again. Sacrifice and suffering are painful indeed, but at the same time also necessary to the completion of the Self. Passively accepting the given Innocence and Grace, may sounds like a state of extreme bliss, but are actually far less romantic than the process of elevation from the deepest pit to the highest heaven with the power of imagination. </p><p>“Fear ye not and behold the Creation of God”, a voice arises in the bottom of heart, retelling the story of Thel.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4313bd0e0a243d4fc1919.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Thel&lt;/em&gt; is one of the prophetic illuminated books written by William Blake, a great British poet, painter and visionary born in the 18th Century. Crafted after &lt;em&gt;The Song of Innocence&lt;/em&gt;, this allegorical poem is closely related to the loss of innocence, perhaps also indicating the creation of &lt;em&gt;The Song of Experience&lt;/em&gt; in the following years.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Book Reviews" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Book-Reviews/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Death &amp; Rebirth</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/21/westwind/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/21/westwind/</id>
    <published>2022-11-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/637b82e816f2c2beb1b4b985.jpg"></p><p>This year, 2022, marks the bicentenary of Percy Bysshe Shelley’s death. Over all the two hundred years, countless fine lines of poetry written by Shelley have continously inspired people to rekindle the fire of hope. But of them all, a particular line from <em>Ode to the West Wind</em> may be the most significant one - “If Winter comes, can Spring be far behind?”. This single line of verse is far more than a rhetorical question concerning the change of seasons, instead, it is as the poet states, a divine prophecy given to those people trapped in states of despair and desolation. </p><span id="more"></span><p><em>Ode to the West Wind</em> consists of five cantos written in terza rima, originally invented by Dante Alighieri and first used in his grand epic poem <em>La Comedia</em>. Apart from the inherited rhyming scheme, there is another deeper layer of connnection between <em>The Divine Comedy</em> and this poem written by Shelley. Winter, like Dante’s Inferno, symbolizes death, while spring, the epitome of Dante’s Paradiso, symbolizes rebirth. Just like withered leaves blasted by the wild west wind are scattered all over the place to quicken a potential new burst of vitality in the upcoming spring, all those terrible sufferings Dante witnesses in Hell also lead him up to a more comprehensive understanding of Life, Light and Love, granting him the vision which enables the once lost Florentine to climb up mount Purgatory and eventually reach the gate of Paradise. Both of these masterpieces produced in Italy implies a universal truth, that descent is also ascent and death actually heralds rebirth.</p><p>Shelley embraced his own death two hundred years ago, drowned sailing in a tempest, but just as shown by the words engraved on his tombstone, a famous line from Shakespeare’s <em>Tempest</em> - “Nothing of him that doth fade, but doth suffer a sea-change, into something rich and strange”, there have indeed risen a thousand beacons from the spark he bores. </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/637b82e816f2c2beb1b4b985.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, 2022, marks the bicentenary of Percy Bysshe Shelley’s death. Over all the two hundred years, countless fine lines of poetry written by Shelley have continously inspired people to rekindle the fire of hope. But of them all, a particular line from &lt;em&gt;Ode to the West Wind&lt;/em&gt; may be the most significant one - “If Winter comes, can Spring be far behind?”. This single line of verse is far more than a rhetorical question concerning the change of seasons, instead, it is as the poet states, a divine prophecy given to those people trapped in states of despair and desolation. &lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
