<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <title>Raptazure&#39;s Space</title>
  
  <subtitle>&quot;Non merita nome di creatore, se non Iddio ed il Poeta.&quot;</subtitle>
  <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  
  <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2025-06-04T14:15:44.196Z</updated>
  <id>http://raptazure.github.io/</id>
  
  <author>
    <name>Raptazure</name>
    
  </author>
  
  <generator uri="https://hexo.io/">Hexo</generator>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Half Mocking and Half Plaintive Calls</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/06/04/the-loons/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/06/04/the-loons/</id>
    <published>2025-06-03T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-06-04T14:15:44.196Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6840538858cb8da5c82cddfd.png"></p><p>&ensp;&ensp;Near the end of <em>The Loons</em>, Vanessa notes that the “long-drawn call” of the birds, described as “half mocking and half plaintive”, has fallen silent across the lake, paralleling Piquette’s tragic death. This loss of sound seems to suggest that the birds and the Métis are destined to share a fate of bitter destruction. However, throughout the passage, if one listens closely, the author’s tone echoes that same mix of mockery and lament. By ridiculing her own deeply ingrained arrogance and indifference toward the Métis and by mourning the oppression and injustice suffered by people like Piquette, the author deconstructs her own racist narrative rather than reinforcing it. What might seem like a racist text is transformed into a sorrowful confession.</p><span id="more"></span><p>&ensp;&ensp;To decide whether a text is racist, we can use a simple criterion: is the critique aimed at the marginalized groups themselves, or is it directed at the marginalizing behaviors of those in power? The former marks a racist text, while the latter marks an anti-racist one. Some critics might argue that emphasizing the tragic fate of the Métis, as a result of white people’s unfair treatment, ends up victimizing them and undermining their strength. However, when one looks at historical records of witch hunts or the atrocities committed by Hitler against the Jews, where the focus is on condemning the tyrants and not beautifying the lives of victims, it becomes increasingly clear that such portrayals are meant to indict the causes of suffering, not to reinforce a static image of victimhood.</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;The subtlety of Laurence’s writing lies in her highly self-conscious choice of the narrative focus, itself mirroring the very process of marginalization. By centering the story on the white girl Vanessa and telling it through her perspective, Piquette’s voice is muted, her emotions concealed, and her story fragmented. This narrative choice, designed to appeal to a white audience (and hopefully make them reflect upon their own biases), reveals just how ingrained the racist lens is in dominant culture. At the same time, the author’s narrative voice is self-conscious and almost self-mocking, as can be seen in Vanessa’s reaction when she learns of Piquette’s impending marriage to an Englishman. It isn’t until then does Vanessa “really see her, for the first and only time in all the years”, that is, not until after Piquette has been assimilated into white society through marriage, at the risk of losing her cultural identity that the white protagonist begins to truly acknowledge her existence as a human being, despite the obvious fact that they had “both lived in the same town” since childhood.</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;By depicting Vanessa’s nearly dehumanizing indifference and blinding arrogance, the text achieves an ironic, almost comically tragic quality. In mocking Vanessa’s willful, almost hyperbolic blindness, the author is also critiquing the limitations of her own narrative strategy. It is only after this moment of “seeing” and self-mockery that the focus gradually shifts to Piquette. Sadly, this shift is triggered only by Piquette’s untimely death — in paragraphs 64 through 69, the story almost exclusively centers on her life, providing the most detailed and intense description of the entire passage, which only intensifies the tragedy, for it is already near the end of the story and definitely too late.</p><p>&ensp;&ensp;This parallel between content and structure reinforces the idea that the tragic fate of the loons, along with the suffering of Piquette and other Métis people, originates not only from the unfair treatment they endure in the story’s world, but also from the text’s own biased portrayal and silencing. Even the reader’s tendency to admire Vanessa and disdain Piquette reflects this dynamic. In this way, by marginalizing and silencing Piquette’s voice, the story becomes a self-critique: the author is not only condemning the marginalizing actions of white characters but is also questioning her own stylistic choices. In writing about the “half mocking and half plaintive” calls of the loons, the author is also expressing the half mocking and half plaintive attitude toward her own narration. In this sense, Laurence’s <em>The Loons</em> is truly anti-racist, in its own subtle but poignant way. </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6840538858cb8da5c82cddfd.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&amp;ensp;&amp;ensp;Near the end of &lt;em&gt;The Loons&lt;/em&gt;, Vanessa notes that the “long-drawn call” of the birds, described as “half mocking and half plaintive”, has fallen silent across the lake, paralleling Piquette’s tragic death. This loss of sound seems to suggest that the birds and the Métis are destined to share a fate of bitter destruction. However, throughout the passage, if one listens closely, the author’s tone echoes that same mix of mockery and lament. By ridiculing her own deeply ingrained arrogance and indifference toward the Métis and by mourning the oppression and injustice suffered by people like Piquette, the author deconstructs her own racist narrative rather than reinforcing it. What might seem like a racist text is transformed into a sorrowful confession.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Literary Wanderings</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/21/literary-wanderings/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/21/literary-wanderings/</id>
    <published>2025-05-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-21T15:05:31.582Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/682dea7858cb8da5c80357f2.jpg"></p><h1 id="Deviation"><a href="#Deviation" class="headerlink" title="Deviation"></a>Deviation</h1><p>Illness and the following recovery often herald the coming of the muses. Both symbolically and physically, these two states mark a deviation from the norm, from the routine, from the familiar, and essentially, according to Shelley’s A Defence of Poetry, possess a quality of poetry in the broader sense of the word. I remember having written a poem about the owl springing from the cage of frost when catching a fever brought by COVID-19; I also remember the ecstasy and vitality brought by recovery which accelerates the movements of the bouncing thoughts inside the skull. What Nietzsche famously wrote in The Gay Science, “Gratitude pours forth continually, as if the unexpected had just happened—the gratitude of a convalescent—for convalescence was unexpected…. The rejoicing of strength that is returning, of a reawakened faith in a tomorrow and the day after tomorrow, of a sudden sense and anticipation of a future, of impending adventures, of seas that are open again”, may indeed act as the source of inspiration, and the joy of life.</p><span id="more"></span><h1 id="Horticultural-Quietism"><a href="#Horticultural-Quietism" class="headerlink" title="Horticultural Quietism"></a>Horticultural Quietism</h1><p><em>Candide</em> of Voltaire:</p><p>The immense power of “cultivating our garden”, of “cultiver notre jardin” - to live in our own small plots instead of the heads of strangers, is extremely relevant in today’s world of flooding information. We need a project. It shouldn’t be too large or dependent on many people. The project should send us to sleep every night, weary but satisfied. It could be bringing up a child, writing a book, looking after a house, running a small shop, managing a little business, or, like the Turk in the book, tending to a few acres. This is the geographic modesty of Voltaire: he advises us to take just a few acres and make those your focus, to take a small orchard and grow lemons and apricots, to take some beds and grow asparagus and carrots, to cultivate a quiet garden that we can truly claim as our own.</p><h1 id="The-World-of-Things"><a href="#The-World-of-Things" class="headerlink" title="The World of Things"></a>The World of Things</h1><p>The Sensitive Plant serves as the medium between things and human, leaning towards the world of things; the Goddess serves as the same medium, only leaning towards the world of human → but to some extent, they all belong to the world of “things”, and not “human” in the sense of mortals → then, is the death of the Goddess a death of mortals, or essentially, a death of things?</p><h1 id="Misinterpretation"><a href="#Misinterpretation" class="headerlink" title="Misinterpretation"></a>Misinterpretation</h1><p>Misplaced interpretation is the violence against genuine literary understanding. How can one take a literary text out of the historical period it was composed in and merely use one’s imagination to haphazardly fill the gaping void between words and their meaning? Creative misreading certainly does not entail the reader’s fantasy can freely roam wherever it pleases, but is still constrained by contextual understanding. The textbook’s interpretation of Hazlitt’s comments on diction, claiming his essay fails to distinguish spoken language and written language by equalling the two, seems to me out of context and does a disservice to the original text, which essentially serves as a champagning essay for the everyday simple diction of the Romantic poetry, especially as exemplified in the Lyrical Ballads.</p><h1 id="Enchantment"><a href="#Enchantment" class="headerlink" title="Enchantment"></a>Enchantment</h1><p>“I’ll follow thee” - Hamlet, Keats</p><p>Hamlet follows his father’s ghost, and Keats  follows the nightingale’s song. </p><p>Hamlet descends into the “insanity” of revenge, and Keats enters into a fairy land forlorn.</p><p>Both enter another realm, another reality; both are enchanted.</p><p>“Of the chameleon’s dish I eat the air” → Shelley’s poet is from <em>Hamlet</em></p><h1 id="Chains-to-Change"><a href="#Chains-to-Change" class="headerlink" title="Chains to Change"></a>Chains to Change</h1><ul><li>Change in Form → poetic drama → focus more on the individual psyche (individual as the starting point)</li><li>From <em>Moira</em> to Moral Agency (the meaning of suffering → to actively forgive, not to passively bear)</li><li>From Power to Love (restraints symbolized by Kratos and Bia → leads to sacrifice (violence towards the self), which is the only way to defy the unchangeable order) (From violence to non-violence, from the physical to the mental&#x2F;spiritual)</li><li>From Tragic Pathos to Romantic Sublime (change in perception of history: from cyclic to progressive)</li><li>From Divine to Human</li></ul><h1 id="Reader-Response"><a href="#Reader-Response" class="headerlink" title="Reader-Response"></a>Reader-Response</h1><p>To practice teaching without students is like applying the reader-response theory to a text without an actual reader. By only imagining the act of someone reading, or in the teacher’s case, listening and responding, the receptor becomes a permanent void, a utilitarian means to help construct and maintain the predetermined structure of the lesson instead of an  end in itself. The receptor remains shapeless till the end, its only residence being the dim regions of the teacher’s egotistic mind. As a result, every action remains a presumption, or even worse, an assumption. In my opinion, the teaching skills truly required for a class, such as spontaneity, sympathy, openness and genuine care towards students can not really be improved through such a highly-wrought and performance-oriented staging of organized fantasy.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/682dea7858cb8da5c80357f2.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h1 id=&quot;Deviation&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Deviation&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Deviation&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Deviation&lt;/h1&gt;&lt;p&gt;Illness and the following recovery often herald the coming of the muses. Both symbolically and physically, these two states mark a deviation from the norm, from the routine, from the familiar, and essentially, according to Shelley’s A Defence of Poetry, possess a quality of poetry in the broader sense of the word. I remember having written a poem about the owl springing from the cage of frost when catching a fever brought by COVID-19; I also remember the ecstasy and vitality brought by recovery which accelerates the movements of the bouncing thoughts inside the skull. What Nietzsche famously wrote in The Gay Science, “Gratitude pours forth continually, as if the unexpected had just happened—the gratitude of a convalescent—for convalescence was unexpected…. The rejoicing of strength that is returning, of a reawakened faith in a tomorrow and the day after tomorrow, of a sudden sense and anticipation of a future, of impending adventures, of seas that are open again”, may indeed act as the source of inspiration, and the joy of life.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Literary Theory" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literary-Theory/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Walking Away from Omelas</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/15/walking-away-from-omelas/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/15/walking-away-from-omelas/</id>
    <published>2025-05-14T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-15T12:18:47.850Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6825dba258cb8da5c8f43c53.png"><br>Beneath the seemingly blissful everyday life of Omelas, there lies a gloomy truth – an innocent child, as the ultimate scapegoat, is bearing the crushing weight of the world in utter loneliness, just like that cursed titan Atlas in Greek mythology, the only difference being the vulnerable child has not rebelled against the vengeful gods. People who choose to stay in Omelas pass by this terror of injustice in silent acquiescence, relinquishing their human agency to make any meaningful ethical decision at all, and insisting that the single sinless child should somehow bear the whole weight of all their moral obligations. Can such a city still be called a utopia, where the goodness and beauty of humanity are cherished and celebrated, when every trace of happiness is sicklied over by the taint of injustice and bad faith?</p><span id="more"></span><p>We have two pieces of framing. First, we characterise “continuing to live in Omelas” as following the existing rules, that is, doing nothing about the child’s suffering. Because Omelas is a utopia characteristically defined by the suffering of a single child and the happiness of all the other citizens, thus changing this determining characteristic would be too radical that it would be no longer suitable to call the reformed city “Omelas” again – it would transform into another kind of utopia all together. Second, by “walking away”, we mean to shoulder our ethical responsibilities and moral agency as a human being again, to deny the justifiability of the innocent scapegoat, and to seek an alternative world, where perhaps everyone’s happiness can be achieved without the suffering of a sinless child, or where at least we can call the weight of our own moral decisions our own and become a truly agential human being.</p><p>We have three substantives. First, we argue that only by walking away from Omelas can people reclaim the full existential entailment of being a human. The dilemma in Omelas is not a mere calculation of lesser evils as exemplified by the famous trolley problem – it is inherently an existential inquiry. The city of Omelas is a predetermined paradise built upon predetermined cruelty, where the child is the only one responsible for all the citizens’ happiness, which the citizens are simply passively enjoying, without really being responsible for it; it is a place where suffering of the child has become not only a moral dilemma, but THE moral dilemma, simply because it is the single one that remains in Omelas – everything else is good and fine; it is a place where every ethical decision is boiled down into one known variable - the unconditional sacrifice of the innocent child, with all the other ethical complexities that being a human entails therefore completely eliminated. As a result, to relinquish the opportunity to act upon such a dilemma, i.e., to choose not to walk away, is to relinquish the possibility to lead an agential life all together; it is to prefer the comfort of a predetermined state of unchallenged perfection instead of embracing the reality of potentiality and freedom, where our ethical decisions can really be called our own, where we can claim “I am good because I have acted righteously”; it is to deny the inherent existential freedom and the corresponding responsibilities of being a human. According to the existential philosopher Jean Paul Satre, an essential part of being a human is exactly that “we are condemned to be free”, that is, at any given moment, we need to make decisions and then be responsible for the consequences of these decisions, which is seemingly a curse, but actually a blessing: the capacity to make hard, painful decisions and to learn from them is indispensable to our continued growth as moral beings. As a result, by walking away, we are refusing to accept such an abdication of moral duty; we are embracing the agency and freedom which is essential for being a human being, or rather, a “human becoming”; we are courageously shouldering the responsibility of shaping our own ethical destiny instead of passively accepting a predetermined sugar-coated injustice like a programmed robot. Comparatively speaking, those who choose to stay are ultimately running away from the pressure of a fully rounded agential life and are thus acting in “bad faith”: they are inherently denying their own freedom, favouring the predetermined ethical answer, merely to alleviate the crushing pressure of being human. The insidious feeling of moral complicity will haunt them after they have realised the inadequacy of such an action, because deep in their hearts, they know they have chosen comfort over conscience and freedom, stability over the heavy but essential burden of ethical decision-making, which makes us fully rounded human beings.</p><p>Second, we argue that only by walking away from Omelas can we begin to expect any possible improvement to happen upon the current situation. The city of Omelas, being a utopia, is by definition, trapped in a state of stasis, because by predefining the evil and the good, it has transcended the dialectical conflicts of history and ethics, becoming more like a concept instead of a city that is continually transforming and developing. According to the existential philosophers in the 19th and 20th centuries, the concept of utopia originates in our deep-rooted desire for stasis, and the existence of Omelas is exactly the fulfilment of our desire to exist in a stable and unchanging situation, which makes it even more alluring. But Ursula’s writing never explicitly states the impossibility of finding a better place in that particular universe, a place where all the happiness can still be enjoyed without the cruel practice of scapegoating. And she never explains the underlying mechanism that links the single child’s confinement with the whole world’s suffering, which makes the necessity of the suffering child rather dubious – maybe even without the child’s confinement, the world would still be fine? Maybe just like the ancient Greek festival Thargelia, the so-called sin-cleansing scapegoats are merely people’s invention to alleviate their own sense of guilt and responsibility? By walking away from Omelas, we are not only sending a symbolic message, but also proving it with our actions that we still believe there can be an alternative world where the “necessary evil” does not exist and we are ready to fight for this ideal, that we are willing to embrace the possibility of creating a new society despite the inherent uncertainty brought by change. Even in the worst scenario, where such an ideal remains nowhere to be found, we can still proudly claim that we prefer to reckon with the consequences of our own actions, to become fully responsible and agential as a human being, rather than passively accept a simplistic, unchanging state of “good” that potentially comes at the expense of our soul. Comparatively speaking, choosing to stay is to be forever trapped in the stasis defined by the very existence of Omelas; it is to live in quiet despair without the freedom or the agency to make the world a potentially better place; it is to surrender in happy ignorance without even trying to seek the alternative. Just like the prisoners in Plato’s cave, the citizens of Omelas, by choosing to forever stay in the cave, will never be able to enjoy the warmth of the sun. By remaining in the eternal stasis of seeming happiness, their disposition is essentially a hopeless one, because all potentialities have been eliminated.</p><p>Third, we argue that by walking away from Omelas, we are standing against the normalisation of cruelty and injustice and showing respect to the inherent dignity of each human being. The child’s suffering is far more than an abstract variable in a utilitarian equation; it is not a disposable cost that can be simply absorbed into a calculus of “the greater good”. Instead, that suffering child is living and breathing, just like every one of us. In fact, continuing to live in Omelas means that even your own child could become the scapegoat and bear the weight of the world in the future. What’s more, those who choose to stay are conveying a symbolic message that such systematic injustice, such a haphazard act of cruelty, is totally acceptable if it is for “the greater good”, that their collective happiness is inherently more valuable than the happiness of a single child. As this rule of scapegoating becomes solidified over time, systematic cruelty will be normalised, and people will fall into a pervasive pattern of moral apathy. In the long term, society might become so accustomed to sacrificing ethical standards for the so-called collective happiness that the distinction between right and wrong, just and unjust, beautiful and ugly will be blurred and compromised. Human history is replete with such bargains, such “necessary evil” that only leads to greater evil. For example, slavery was once thought by many as a “necessary evil”, which was indispensable for economic growth and the stability of the social order. The cruelty and injustice towards slaves were justified on utilitarian grounds: in many people’s eyes, the immense profits and rapid development brought by slavery simply outweighed the potential moral repugnance. However, in the long term, this “necessary evil” only led to more evils – it sown the seeds of systematic racism and civil unrest that still troubles many countries even today. By walking away from Omelas, we are saying the normalization and apathy towards cruelty is categorically false, no matter how “necessary” it may appear; we are saying the cost of a “perfect” society – when perfection is tainted with the blood of innocent children and the enforcement of systematic injustice - is too high a price for human dignity.</p><p>Therefore, we argue that walking away from the veiled terror of Omelas and trying to seek an alternative world is infinitely more preferable.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/6825dba258cb8da5c8f43c53.png&quot;&gt;&lt;br&gt;Beneath the seemingly blissful everyday life of Omelas, there lies a gloomy truth – an innocent child, as the ultimate scapegoat, is bearing the crushing weight of the world in utter loneliness, just like that cursed titan Atlas in Greek mythology, the only difference being the vulnerable child has not rebelled against the vengeful gods. People who choose to stay in Omelas pass by this terror of injustice in silent acquiescence, relinquishing their human agency to make any meaningful ethical decision at all, and insisting that the single sinless child should somehow bear the whole weight of all their moral obligations. Can such a city still be called a utopia, where the goodness and beauty of humanity are cherished and celebrated, when every trace of happiness is sicklied over by the taint of injustice and bad faith?&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Debate" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Debate/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Fragments of Thoughts - A Journey Downward and Upward</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/08/fragments-of-thoughts/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/05/08/fragments-of-thoughts/</id>
    <published>2025-05-07T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:46:10.598Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb3e658cb8da5c8e6665f.png"></p><h3 id="The-Downfall"><a href="#The-Downfall" class="headerlink" title="The Downfall"></a>The Downfall</h3><p>(2025.5.4) Every age has its own plight, and the relentless consumption of media is one of ours. In the vast expanse of cyberspace, many of us have succumbed to a peculiar kind of gluttony—a ceaseless craving perpetuated by the bombardment of video games, anime, provocative content, and endless streams of short videos. This insatiable beast, ever hungrier after feeding, has not only eaten away our time, but more importantly, our mind—our ability to concentrate is eroded, replaced by a constant pursuit of the new and the stimulating; the passage of time, once a steady flow, now feels disjointed and surreally fleeting; our experiences, once cohesively expanding throughout the day, have fragmented into foggy moments clouded by digital haze; creativity, the expression of the human spirit, lies dormant under the weight of passive indulgence and mindless binging. Yet the cruel irony remains: when we look back and examine what lingers after consuming such an astounding amount of content, we are often met with a mocking devil gesturing at us—a blank page and the quiet void of oblivion!</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="The-Cave"><a href="#The-Cave" class="headerlink" title="The Cave"></a>The Cave</h3><p>(2025.5.3) But still, we have social relations, and are thus constrained by societal expectations. We still have to strive for worldly things, to vie for power, to brandish our titles and our trophies for the world to see. Is it possible, to throw away all the forms of external confinements imposed by the society, the mind-forged manacles that serve as the source for our unhappiness? Unless we can crawl inside a cave, and remain solitary forever until the world forgets us, together with the dim shadows that we have cast. But that would be death and annihilation for the man floating amidst a sea of islands and the birth of a new land only lit by its own mind. (Note: But Blake managed to let his inner mind illuminate the world.)</p><h3 id="The-Ascent"><a href="#The-Ascent" class="headerlink" title="The Ascent"></a>The Ascent</h3><p>(2025.5.6) Dante intends to climb up the glorious mountain of felicity but is instead scared to death by the three beasts guarding the ascending path. Similarly, procrastination is born out of fear, doubt and the sense of being overwhelmed. It is the self-admitted defeat even before the battle begins. It is the poison tree growing from stagnant water, accumulating toxins around its roots, and preparing to release its paralytic effects upon the human mind that nurtures it with the tempting escapism rooted in conscious infirmity and unconscious despair. How should we, then, liberate ourselves from this abominable paralysis, these heavy chains of inertia? Step by step, as we reclaim our autonomy with glittering hope, unyielding courage, and an adamant will to power, even the direst situation may begin to change for the better. Perhaps, beneath the everlasting flux of things, there runs a golden stream of cause and effect that guides us towards our destination, the fragrant blossoming meadows along it patiently inviting us to tread upon.</p><h3 id="The-Fate"><a href="#The-Fate" class="headerlink" title="The Fate"></a>The Fate</h3><p>(2025.5.7) Fate, with her stately commands and veiled visage, comes upon our door and silently knocks. She is seeking the Sun inside every one of us, the Sun that can dispel all the lurking darkness and thaw all the biting frost, the Sun that can make even the most tedious days of Sisyphus seem joyous and worthwhile, the Sun that rises eternally inside and continues to illuminate everything outside. This is the process of soul-making, of finding your Sun.</p><h3 id="The-Finalite"><a href="#The-Finalite" class="headerlink" title="The Finalité"></a>The Finalité</h3><p>(2025.5.3) Words are uttered, and after that, they cannot stay; they slip away like a speeded snail, leaving only the faint echoes of vague sounds. Words, once written, have already began to live a posthumous existence. As for the answers, they can only be found after the finalité.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb3e658cb8da5c8e6665f.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;The-Downfall&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#The-Downfall&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;The Downfall&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Downfall&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;(2025.5.4) Every age has its own plight, and the relentless consumption of media is one of ours. In the vast expanse of cyberspace, many of us have succumbed to a peculiar kind of gluttony—a ceaseless craving perpetuated by the bombardment of video games, anime, provocative content, and endless streams of short videos. This insatiable beast, ever hungrier after feeding, has not only eaten away our time, but more importantly, our mind—our ability to concentrate is eroded, replaced by a constant pursuit of the new and the stimulating; the passage of time, once a steady flow, now feels disjointed and surreally fleeting; our experiences, once cohesively expanding throughout the day, have fragmented into foggy moments clouded by digital haze; creativity, the expression of the human spirit, lies dormant under the weight of passive indulgence and mindless binging. Yet the cruel irony remains: when we look back and examine what lingers after consuming such an astounding amount of content, we are often met with a mocking devil gesturing at us—a blank page and the quiet void of oblivion!&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Society" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Society/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Resentment</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/04/28/on-resentment/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/04/28/on-resentment/</id>
    <published>2025-04-27T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T12:11:04.308Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681c9f4e58cb8da5c8e62fbc.png"></p><p>Resentment refers to the bitter indignation at having been treated unfairly. By examining this definition, it is easy to identify the two indispensable components of this emotional state – “having been treated unfairly” as the external event that triggers such an emotion, and “bitter indignation” as the internal response towards such an event.</p><span id="more"></span><p>In order to dive into the complex and interlocking causal chain behind such a reaction, first, let us focus on the imagined root cause of this emotion, the said “culprit” who is out of our control. This silent burying of anger and bitterness originates in the belief that everyone, especially us, should be treated fairly. But, how do we define “fairness” in such a context? Due to the partial nature of subjectivity, we tend to subconsciously ascribe the attribute of fairness to many things that are simply <em>desirable</em> for us, especially when we have made an exertion to get them, or the undesirable outcome involves certain violation of rules in our opinion. When the ideal scenario fails to manifest itself in the real life, we think that we do not deserve to be treated so poorly. But the thing is, can this particular interpretation of fairness represent all different forms of fairness? If we dwell upon the fairness of God, or Nature, it might be another story altogether – everything inherently obeys the law of nature, including the people who give us an “unfair” jurisdiction. Our strive for fairness shares the same psychological root that motivates these people to treat us in a seemingly unfair way. Yes, maybe they are trying to deprive us of self-esteem and even happiness. But are they not doing it out of their own psychological deficiencies, such as incompetence, fear, or insecurity? Those who inflicts suffering suffer intensely, and the best defense is not to allow such negativity to eat away our felicity, so that the wrathful fire can only burn the stone-throwers.</p><p>Second, let’s focus on the relationship between the internal emotional state and the external event. Is resentment the necessary outcome of being treated unfairly? The answer is seemingly true because we are all culturally programmed to believe that is the case. When we were young, we learned from our parents or teachers that the feeling of bitterness and anger after being unjustly treated is perfectly justified, or rather, it is actually the only “normal” reaction of a living and breathing human being. But that does not make it as inevitable as the force of gravity which makes us stand on the ground, because instead of acting as a force of nature, it acts through cultural conditioning. Imagine, two group of people are from two distinct cultures. The first group are constantly told that everything happens to them represents the will of a divine being, and eventually everything will make sense through the interactions of a very complex web of interrelated events. And the second group are constantly reminded that bad things happen to them because they are not competent enough, or because other people want to harm them for whatever reason. It is easy to imagine the vast difference in attitudes and reactions when these two groups of people are put into the same situation. Suppose they <strong>think</strong> they are ****unfairly treated by the judge in a football match. The first group will try to reason out the underlying meaning and implications behind such a treatment, leading to more patient understanding before any rash actions, while the second group will tend to become instantly antagonistic towards the judge, dwelling upon their anger and bitterness, maybe eventually become so occupied by these negative thoughts that they decide to unleash a savage verbal attack towards the judge without sufficiently reflecting upon their own potential deficiencies.</p><p>Now that we have discussed: 1) our perception of being treated unfairly might originate in the varying definitions of fairness and the highly subjective nature of our experience; 2) the feeling of bitter anger is not the inevitable result of external events, but rather, it is established and reinforced by repetitive cultural conditioning which works in the subconscious level and becomes automatic in our emotional responses. Then, the key question becomes, how do we avoid being resentful after experiencing such events? First, being aware of the cultural conditioning involved in our emotional responses is the essential first step towards improvement. Instead of serving as the exercise of our free will and the fuel for our well-being, resentment is more likely to be the product of the unconscious following of the band-wagon, the “mutiny within”. Second, realize that our mental well-being is still within our grasp, and if after taking all the plausible actions, the injustice remains unchanged, then suspend the judgement of its effects might be more reasonable, because on one knows whether it will lead to bliss or bane amidst the complex web of events. By doing so, we choose to remain open before the unknown, recognize the interrelatedness of everything, and acknowledge that all is involved in the continuous creation of <em>Deus sive Natura.</em></p><p><em>Note: this piece of writing is an experiment of adopting Utilitarianism and Spinozist metaphysics to alleviate the pain brought by resentment, and does not necessarily reflect the author’s full take on this subject – if you are one of those artists, whose focus must be vastly different, leaning towards the creation of beauty based on experience and understanding, seeking to transform the grotesque into the beautiful instead of merely trying to comprehend the birth of resentment in the intellectual level, then this article can perhaps only serve as an interesting thought experiment, for your burden, your mission, your thorny paths of roses, lie elsewhere.</em></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681c9f4e58cb8da5c8e62fbc.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Resentment refers to the bitter indignation at having been treated unfairly. By examining this definition, it is easy to identify the two indispensable components of this emotional state – “having been treated unfairly” as the external event that triggers such an emotion, and “bitter indignation” as the internal response towards such an event.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Psychology" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Psychology/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Poetry Reading</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/03/10/on-poetry-reading/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/03/10/on-poetry-reading/</id>
    <published>2025-03-09T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:11:27.374Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca26058cb8da5c8e635cb.png"></p><blockquote><p><em>“When there is poetry,<br>it is Orpheus singing. He lightly comes and goes.”<br>                                                  - Rainer Maria Rilke</em></p></blockquote><p>Poetry reading is one of the most enriching of all social activities. And it is an activity uniquely human. Despite the myriads of ways a nightingale or a skylark sings to the fading night or the rising morn, they do not indulge in anything that could be called the chanting of poems, those sweetest songs of humanity that often “tell of saddest thought”.</p><span id="more"></span><p>The allure of poetry reading lies in its ability to unite and to enchant, to reconjure what is beautiful collectively. A group of people assemble around the table, like in an ancient Greek symposium. Together or one by one, they chant poems about death, love, war and peace, allowing the music of words to pierce the guarded wit and pass into the panting heart beneath. Poetry reading does not commence from a fixed point, and no one anticipates where the flow of verses might lead as it weaves and dances, ignites or simply glows. The foe of a captivating poetry reading is the individual who insists on deciphering every single line. Poetry reading is not about solving a complex puzzle; it is like diving into a lake, with an aim not to “immediately swim to the shore”, but to “luxuriate in the sensation of water”. There is no intellectual victory or defeat in poetry reading. In truth, the finest participants are those willing to embrace endless ambiguities and succumb to the musical flow of sounds. Just when people think they have grasped the essence of a stanza or made acquittance with a poem, the next rereading unfolds, adding a brand new layer of meaning and possibilities. They are ready to start anew.</p><p>Perhaps it is owing to my experiences in intimate bookshop gatherings that I find poetry readings possess a unique charm. The fellow attendees are not deeply entwined in each other’s personal narratives. Instead, they choose to completely immerse in the world of poetry, to give those mending hearts, unspoken fears, burning desires and hidden vulnerabilities a local habitation and a name. Together, they chant poems; together, they chant their souls. No more words are needed; silence can tend to the rest. This is the unutterable bliss of poetry reading.</p><p></br></br><br>附：小诗一首 —— 《门》</p><p>她静静地走向那扇门。<br>那扇孤寂的、长满青苔的铁的造物，<br>上面突兀地镌刻着“Amor Fati”。<br>于她而言，<br>那无疑是冰冷的，以至于封隔世界的存在。</p><p>第一次叩响。无言。<br>指节与金属相撞的声音，不断震荡在门的身躯里。<br>回环的、扩散的音波，却只被沉寂回应，<br>一如她被尘压在门后的记忆。</p><p>第二次叩响。微弱的、颤动的“啊”<br>扭动着如蛆虫从门后传来，<br>似哀鸣，似长叹，<br>似被黑夜升起的浓烟遮掩的呼吸。</p><p>第三次叩响。沉重的、斥责的“莫”<br>夹杂着拒绝与死的威严，<br>似警戒，似劝言，<br>似被晨雾包裹的一瞬的露珠。</p><p>第四次叩响。腾跃的、自由的“法”<br>直行着、坚决地穿透了钢铁，<br>似抚慰，似告诫，<br>似被正午的太阳许诺的追逐。</p><p>第五次叩响。终结的、延续的“啼”<br>回转着、围绕了全世界，<br>似轻语，似梦呓，<br>似被黄昏念想晕染的霞与月。</p><p>即将叩响的手指悬停。<br>门静伫依然。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca26058cb8da5c8e635cb.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;“When there is poetry,&lt;br&gt;it is Orpheus singing. He lightly comes and goes.”&lt;br&gt;                                                  - Rainer Maria Rilke&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Poetry reading is one of the most enriching of all social activities. And it is an activity uniquely human. Despite the myriads of ways a nightingale or a skylark sings to the fading night or the rising morn, they do not indulge in anything that could be called the chanting of poems, those sweetest songs of humanity that often “tell of saddest thought”.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Forgetfulness</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/23/on-forgetfulness/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/23/on-forgetfulness/</id>
    <published>2025-02-22T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:33:09.491Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681caa9558cb8da5c8e64fd3.png"></p><p>As human beings, we tend to forget things, sometimes rather quickly and against our will. We reach out our hands, often quite desperately, to grasp the precious moment as it slips away. We take photos, write notes, and try so hard to bore our eyes into the ephemeral nature of things.  </p><span id="more"></span><p>Forgetfulness explains and justifies so many seemingly bizarre behaviours of human beings that might never be comprehended or apprehended by gods or animals alike. It is deeply related to being mortal, experiencing this limited existence, which only lasts for a few thousand days and is no more.</p><p>Some say that it is not how things happen to us that really matters, but how we choose to perceive or experience them. As for the representations of things in our memory, maybe it is not how we actually experience them that matters, but how we choose to remember them, to commemorate them that really counts. We can bequeath the fleeting shadows of the shattered past with the most beautiful wreath of flowers; we can weave what was and what is into a carefully crafted personal anthology of subjective revaluation; we can contextualise and transform our unique history into a continuum of multiplying identities and expanding selves. Our memory, as it slowly fades away, can yet become so much more, with the glow of imagination and the flow of narration.</p><blockquote><p>“These were the pranks she played among the cities<br>Of mortal men, and what she did to Sprites<br>And Gods, entangling them in her sweet ditties<br>To do her will, and show their subtle sleights,<br>I will declare another time; for it is<br>A tale more fit for the weird winter nights<br>Than for these garish summer days, when we<br>Scarcely believe much more than we can see.”<sup>1</sup></p></blockquote><h2 id="References"><a href="#References" class="headerlink" title="References"></a>References</h2><p><sup>1</sup>Percy Shelley, <em>The Witch of Atlas</em>, Line 665.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681caa9558cb8da5c8e64fd3.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As human beings, we tend to forget things, sometimes rather quickly and against our will. We reach out our hands, often quite desperately, to grasp the precious moment as it slips away. We take photos, write notes, and try so hard to bore our eyes into the ephemeral nature of things.  &lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Be the Master of Technology</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/20/the-master-of-technology/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/02/20/the-master-of-technology/</id>
    <published>2025-02-19T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T12:56:27.137Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca8dc58cb8da5c8e6495e.png"></p><h3 id="Introduction"><a href="#Introduction" class="headerlink" title="Introduction"></a>Introduction</h3><p>In today’s world of booming technologies, we face a serious problem: how to effectively utilise technology so that we can become its master instead of its slave.</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="Looking-back"><a href="#Looking-back" class="headerlink" title="Looking back"></a>Looking back</h3><p>I believe many people have similar experiences: in a dark room, lying prostrate on the bed, scrolling the phone endlessly, not doing anything particularly, I am merely trying to extend the length of the day, of course, in vain. As time flies, I find this bad habit particularly pernicious, for it harms not only our eyes but also our brain, draining the energy originally prepared for a new day. Now, I have decided to change.</p><h3 id="Moving-forward"><a href="#Moving-forward" class="headerlink" title="Moving forward"></a>Moving forward</h3><p>To master technology instead of being mastered by it, we need to pay attention to everyday details, the so-called “minute particulars”, to quote William Blake’s words, for there lies the secrets of habit formation.</p><p>For me, desktop OS (Windows&#x2F;MacOS&#x2F;Linux) means productivity, while Android&#x2F;iOS implies consumption, mainly because of the differences in terms of interaction mode and application ecosystem. On a computer, one can simply do more things, and the multitasking capacity is also considerably higher than that of a phone; one is more inclined to use keyboard and trackpad&#x2F;mouse, which makes the act of using the device more consciously done than scrolling and tapping almost unconsciously on a phone.</p><p>Next comes the question - what kinds of computers then? To adapt to various scenarios, the device should be versatile and light, elegantly designed and enjoyable to use; ideally, it should be both a computer and a mobile device, so that most scenarios that require a touchscreen can also be covered. After applying all these filters, the answer seems rather obvious to me -  Microsoft Surface Pro, which is both a computer and a tablet, with a detachable keyboard cover and an attachable digital pen, making it one of the most versatile devices available on the market. Most games are not suitable for running on this device, which can be a good thing for productivity.</p><h3 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h3><p>Of course, choosing the appropriate device is just the beginning; what comes next may be more important - use the device to experience and to create more beautiful and meaningful things.</p><p>I desire to go back to the olden ways of interacting with virtual worlds - books and a computer.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681ca8dc58cb8da5c8e6495e.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;Introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#Introduction&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;Introduction&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Introduction&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;In today’s world of booming technologies, we face a serious problem: how to effectively utilise technology so that we can become its master instead of its slave.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Technology" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Technology/"/>
    
    <category term="Lifestyle" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Lifestyle/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>诗四首：春交响</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2025/01/18/four-poems-spring/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2025/01/18/four-poems-spring/</id>
    <published>2025-01-17T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43ef0d0e0a243d4fc1be1.jpg"></p><h3 id="一、骨笛"><a href="#一、骨笛" class="headerlink" title="一、骨笛"></a>一、骨笛</h3><center>欢快与忧伤在心中流淌，<p>这远古悠扬的乐音，来自何方？</p></br><p>当人类生的呼吸贯通你死的鸣腔，</p><p>每一丝破裂的纹路，都盈满空气的激荡。</p><span id="more"></span></br><p>于是我听到，那静谧的死亡，仍在生长。</p><p>你倔强的骨节，决意奏出灵魂的鸣响。</p></br><p>几百年过去，歇落的只是反抗的奢望，</p><p>顺应了自然的构想，</p><p>此刻的你，不也仍在飞翔，仍在歌唱？</p></br><h3 id="二、春日繁花"><a href="#二、春日繁花" class="headerlink" title="二、春日繁花"></a>二、春日繁花</h3><p>从混沌的沼泽扯出金色的丝线，</p><p>将寄居此处溺亡的泥泞，</p><p>都凝成编织春日繁花的梦境。</p></br><h3 id="三、命运"><a href="#三、命运" class="headerlink" title="三、命运"></a>三、命运</h3><p>在旷野中寻找命运</p><p>那摇晃的恍如永恒的一刹。</p></br><p>Amor Fati… Amor Fati…</p><p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a45fb0d0e0a243d4fc2a89.webp" alt="img"></p></br><h3 id="四、愚神的春日"><a href="#四、愚神的春日" class="headerlink" title="四、愚神的春日"></a>四、愚神的春日</h3><p>我于愚神的春日醒来，</p><p>四方已然落花一片，流水无言。</p><p>远去的幻影朦胧如烟，</p><p>晕散在樱染的暮帘。</p></br><p>什么可以抓得住？</p><p>怎样才能不忘却？</p><p>这独属我的小房间。</p><p>在目送过无数流连的眼，</p><p>终于还是，</p><p>唯有这春日相伴。</center></p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43ef0d0e0a243d4fc1be1.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;一、骨笛&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#一、骨笛&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;一、骨笛&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;一、骨笛&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;欢快与忧伤在心中流淌，

&lt;p&gt;这远古悠扬的乐音，来自何方？&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/br&gt;

&lt;p&gt;当人类生的呼吸贯通你死的鸣腔，&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;每一丝破裂的纹路，都盈满空气的激荡。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="诗歌" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E8%AF%97%E6%AD%8C/"/>
    
    <category term="文学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E6%96%87%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="写作" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%86%99%E4%BD%9C/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Six Poems - Dreamy Nights</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2024/06/30/six-poems-dreamy-nights/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2024/06/30/six-poems-dreamy-nights/</id>
    <published>2024-06-29T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.556Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43d5fd0e0a243d4fc1b7d.jpg"></p><h3 id="I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep"><a href="#I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep" class="headerlink" title="I. The Bells of Black Sheep"></a>I. The Bells of Black Sheep</h3><center><p>Dark clouds congregate across the sky</p><p>Of crystal blue, where a fragile butterfly</p><p>Attempts to soar high with golden wings</p><p>For vain hope, swirling and flitting in the wind.</p><span id="more"></span></br><p>Above the clouds twenty sheep solemnly stand,</p><p>Proud their mien, regal even, like the ministers</p><p>Heralding demise, those from that mysterious land</p><p>Of decay and despair, tolling the bells of disaster.</p><p>The sound is slow and heavy, pulsating like heartbeats</p><p>Which blindly run through the threads of creation</p><p>And end with a knit of mighty necessity, leaving</p><p>Visages pale, wings broken and hearts drown in emotion.</p></br><p>The faerie butterfly, beholding the upcoming abyss,</p><p>Calmly accepts her destiny, and begins to dream</p><p>The sweetest dream she could ever conceive,</p><p>A dream of blooming flowers dancing,</p><p>Of music flowing, infants smiling,</p><p>Of moonlight shining, suns rising,</p><p>Of Garden of Eden endowed with original beauty,</p><p>Everything joyfully living.</p></br><p>Fear dissipates in the reverie of hope,</p><p>And bells seem to cease for its sake, idling</p><p>Away the hours of their noonday, considering</p><p>The possibility of a starlit night, though fleeting,</p><p>With the most astonishing display</p><p>Of butterfly dance, which can illuminate</p><p>Even the darkest dale in the universe.</p></br><p>The flood of light effuses from the sky.</p></br><h3 id="II-A-Bee’s-Escapism"><a href="#II-A-Bee’s-Escapism" class="headerlink" title="II. A Bee’s Escapism"></a>II. A Bee’s Escapism</h3><p>Here comes a golden bee, </p><p>Fleeing from its drenchèd flight, </p><p>Buzzing round a pile of dung.</p></br><p>O, fair dweller of sweet fragrance, </p><p>When thy wings to heaviness sink, </p><p>Thou dost choose a jail of stink, </p><p>To escape the wearied voyage</p></br><p>In a humid day</p><p>Of battering rain.</p></br><h3 id="III-Nightsong"><a href="#III-Nightsong" class="headerlink" title="III. Nightsong"></a>III. Nightsong</h3><p>The day departs. Two mournful shadows rise</p><p>With voices vain and gloomy, blowing death.</p><p>Their bones decay, their heavy steps surmise</p><p>The dreary fears that men dare not confess.</p><p>Until a lance of light is thrown through night,</p><p>Diffusing odours sweet as blooming rose,</p><p>Then they dissolve like morning dew in flight</p><p>Of dread, and find in tombs eterne repose.</p><p>The chaste and gentle moon of Love ascends</p><p>In perfect glory, shining dizzy beams</p><p>On those resentful phantoms’ timely ends,</p><p>Dispersing haunting dreams with silver gleams.</p><p>The spinning wheel of life then rolls apace,</p><p>Across the land serene, in endless grace.</p></br><h3 id="IV-Mystical-Pageantry"><a href="#IV-Mystical-Pageantry" class="headerlink" title="IV. Mystical Pageantry"></a>IV. Mystical Pageantry</h3><p>Many a bird is singing in the forest</p><p>Of reverie and mirth, with various music</p><p>Floating through the decaying trees deformed</p><p>By endless battering of dragging years.</p></br><p>Pageants of Queens and Kings bizzarely march</p><p>With solemn precision and knightly strength</p><p>Penetrating the trembling air of morning</p><p>And piercing through the mystery of summer.</p></br><h3 id="V-Blackbird"><a href="#V-Blackbird" class="headerlink" title="V. Blackbird"></a>V. Blackbird</h3><p>A blackbird hops along the street, her steps</p><p>Tender and light, her eyes amass the breath</p><p>Of gentle purple dawn and crimson sun</p><p>Of June, the loving prophecy of life,</p><p>Delicate forms of nature’s patient art.</p></br><p>O, thou embassador of Endless Rhymes!</p><p>Thy song transcends the petty scope of minds</p><p>And flies across the slow and crawling Time,</p><p>Towards the region strange, unknown, sublime,</p><p>A heart renewed, a forehead divine!</p></br><h3 id="VI-Crescendo"><a href="#VI-Crescendo" class="headerlink" title="VI. Crescendo"></a>VI. Crescendo</h3><p>O, Gentle Soul,</p><p>Gently breathing sorrow,</p></br><p>Sighing like a Deluge foretold</p><p>By the Lightening fierce and bold</p><p>Bursting through the purple Nights of Old</p></br><p>Before the Crescent Moon wore her garments cold.</p></br></center>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43d5fd0e0a243d4fc1b7d.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#I-The-Bells-of-Black-Sheep&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;I. The Bells of Black Sheep&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;I. The Bells of Black Sheep&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;center&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dark clouds congregate across the sky&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of crystal blue, where a fragile butterfly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Attempts to soar high with golden wings&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For vain hope, swirling and flitting in the wind.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
    <category term="Art" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Art/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>On Governmental Patronage in the Development of the Arts</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2024/02/10/on-governmental-patronage-for-the-development-of-arts/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2024/02/10/on-governmental-patronage-for-the-development-of-arts/</id>
    <published>2024-02-09T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-05-08T13:54:00.630Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb10458cb8da5c8e66054.png"></p><p>A vagabond wanders alone through the streets, clutching a drawing board in his hand, still chasing after the elusive God of Art with eyes eager to discover beauty. He is, undeniably, a drifter in the age of materialism—a living embodiment of the “poor artist” archetype, one often dismissed as an outcast, yet standing as an unyielding testament to creative perseverance. This image may evoke heartache and dismay, yet it is also the reality that many artists in modern society face, navigating an existence where passion must battle pragmatism. However, with government support, artists can sustain their craft, and their livelihoods may be preserved. In my view, such an act is not merely generous—it is an affirmation of the intrinsic value of artistic expression in human civilization.</p><span id="more"></span><h3 id="The-Symbolic-Relationship-Between-Art-and-Civilization"><a href="#The-Symbolic-Relationship-Between-Art-and-Civilization" class="headerlink" title="The Symbolic Relationship Between Art and Civilization"></a>The Symbolic Relationship Between Art and Civilization</h3><p>The skepticism surrounding government assistance for artists stems largely from a utilitarian approach to economics—one that prioritizes industrial advancement and scientific progress above cultural investment. Opponents argue that national wealth should be directed toward infrastructure, technology, and scientific discovery, which, in their view, are the true engines of modern progress. Yet, history tells a different tale—one that reminds us that the progress of humanity is never solely measured by material wealth or technological milestones, but also by the intangible brilliance of creativity and culture.</p><p>The Renaissance offers one of history’s most compelling counterexamples. Without the House of Medici generously funding talented yet struggling artists, the world may never have known the genius of Leonardo da Vinci, the architectural grandeur of Gothic cathedrals, or the poetic depth of Botticelli’s “Primavera.” Their patronage did more than sustain the livelihoods of painters and sculptors—it ignited a cultural revolution, one that reshaped philosophy, literature, and political thought. Florence, through its investment in the arts, became a beacon of intellectual and artistic excellence, a city remembered through the ages not merely for its economic prosperity but for its contributions to human expression and ingenuity.</p><h3 id="Economic-and-Social-Implications"><a href="#Economic-and-Social-Implications" class="headerlink" title="Economic and Social Implications"></a>Economic and Social Implications</h3><p>Beyond historical precedent, contemporary society continues to thrive on artistic innovation. While opponents may argue that the arts do not yield immediate financial returns, the cultural industry proves otherwise. Cities known for their artistic vibrancy—Paris, Florence, Beijing—are not just cultural landmarks but thriving economic hubs, drawing millions of tourists, investors, and scholars each year. The presence of renowned artists elevates a city’s status, transforming it into a space of both economic and intellectual exchange.</p><p>Furthermore, supporting artists is not merely an economic strategy; it is an act of human solidarity. Given the unpredictable nature of creative work, many artists struggle at the outset of their careers, making financial assistance not only beneficial but, at times, essential. Often, all an artistic genius needs is a fertile space to grow. Without such encouragement, countless potential masterpieces may remain unrealized, lost to history due to the crushing weight of financial instability.</p><h3 id="The-Transformative-Power-of-Art"><a href="#The-Transformative-Power-of-Art" class="headerlink" title="The Transformative Power of Art"></a>The Transformative Power of Art</h3><p>Art is more than an aesthetic endeavor—it shapes ideology, inspires revolutions, and expands the boundaries of human consciousness. Literature, film, music, and visual arts all serve as conduits through which societies explore identity, challenge norms, and foster unity. A nation that invests in its artists is not merely subsidizing individuals; it is cultivating visionaries who will shape the collective imagination of generations to come.</p><p>Consider the transformative power of the Harlem Renaissance, in which Black artists, writers, and musicians redefined cultural narratives and reshaped dialogues on race and identity. Consider the impact of Picasso’s “Guernica,” a painting that transcended canvas to become a political statement against war. Consider the literary power of James Joyce or Gabriel García Márquez—authors whose works provided entire nations with voices that resonated beyond borders. Without support, many of these figures may never have reached their potential. And without artistic expression, societies risk stagnation—trapped in an existence devoid of reflection, storytelling, or emotional depth.</p><h3 id="Conclusion"><a href="#Conclusion" class="headerlink" title="Conclusion"></a>Conclusion</h3><p>Government support for artists is not merely an act of generosity—it is an investment in the intellectual, emotional, and cultural growth of a nation. It is a commitment to the idea that progress is not merely technological or economic, but also creative and philosophical. It ensures that future generations inherit a legacy rich not only in scientific discovery but in artistic brilliance—the paintings, literature, music, and architecture that shape human history as profoundly as any invention.</p><p>Florence did not ascend to greatness through commerce alone, nor did Paris earn its reputation solely through industrial success. They flourished because they believed in art, nurtured it, and let it transform their cities into spaces of wonder and thought. Thus, supporting the arts is not just worthwhile—it is necessary.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/681cb10458cb8da5c8e66054.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A vagabond wanders alone through the streets, clutching a drawing board in his hand, still chasing after the elusive God of Art with eyes eager to discover beauty. He is, undeniably, a drifter in the age of materialism—a living embodiment of the “poor artist” archetype, one often dismissed as an outcast, yet standing as an unyielding testament to creative perseverance. This image may evoke heartache and dismay, yet it is also the reality that many artists in modern society face, navigating an existence where passion must battle pragmatism. However, with government support, artists can sustain their craft, and their livelihoods may be preserved. In my view, such an act is not merely generous—it is an affirmation of the intrinsic value of artistic expression in human civilization.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Writings" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Writings/"/>
    
    <category term="Arts" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Arts/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>论「混沌」</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/08/24/on-chaos/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/08/24/on-chaos/</id>
    <published>2023-08-23T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.552Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43cb7d0e0a243d4fc1b3c.jpg"></p><p>大地颤动着，似乎要吞噬伫立其上的一切：高耸的楼台，抑或青翠的密林，酣然的沉睡，抑或迷途的心。一切都被某种不可抗拒的力量禁锢，拉入一种更原始、更未经分化的状态。这是多元现象世界的塌落，是于虚无中走向统一的深渊。『混沌』是人类赋予它的名字。</p><span id="more"></span><p>在各地的神话与符号象征之中，随处可见『混沌』的踪迹。从奥维德变形记中所描绘的世界伊始，“自然的面庞在何处都别无二致，只是未经分割的无生命之物，却又潜藏着无数未来的种子与互相争斗的元素力”；到弥尔顿失乐园中撒旦所跌落的境界之地，“是天之外的冥荒与无尽的暗夜，沸腾的湖面上升腾起黑色火焰，灼烧着这片被迷失笼罩的无光之地”，『混沌』在任何时代，似乎都牵动着人们想象力中更加隐晦和神秘的部分，又好像在解释着一些不可言说的终极。在一些人眼里，『混沌』是沉重的命运，是对个体存在的否定，是崩坏的终极；在另一些人眼里，『混沌』是原初的希冀，是创造的前奏，是最后的归一。</p><p>但在各种对于『混沌』的想象与解释中，若能抽出一根丝线尝试将它们串联到一起，那大概会是『一元』，只不过这里的一元，潜藏着太多未知与黑暗、矛盾与野蛮，不同于另一极的秩序世界所注强调的灵与智能的统一，这里更多强调的则是形与物质的未分化。然而对于作为初状态的『混沌』而言，这样被混乱裹挟的空间，或者说连空间都不足以称得存在的状态，却同时也是孕育创造的地方。正因为这层虚空，一切可能性都有了潜在的居所，一切妄为的自由都被保证，一切崭新的开始都被承认，这层『无』是之后无数『有』的开端，是一颗包含了无限的种子，是所有故事最初的摇篮。而意义，也就必然从这虚无之中降生，正如诗句从潜意识的深渊奔涌而出一样，带着所有可能的光与热，美与希望，流向这世界。</p><p>而对于末状态的『混沌』而言，情况则看起来悲观得多，作为一切的湮灭，那意味着尘归尘，或者归于更加不可被辨别的物质，意味着发散到未知的时间与空间，意味着死亡。而这，又是否真的是最后的终极？人类或许穷尽无数个世纪都无法确定这个问题的答案。然而，我们却隐隐约约地感受到，在那之后的混沌中，仍会有如同之前一般互相争斗的元素，仍有着无数关于未来的种子与生命的可能，有着未实现的新的开端。也许，从古代流传下来的 Ouroboros（衔尾蛇）的形象就是于『混沌』之中走来，遍历了无尽的历史、现在与未来之后，归于混沌的沉寂，又开始混沌的新生，循环往复，不断轮回，如同旋转的无限，将自己的存在映射于宇宙的意识之上。</p><p>而『混沌』，也会凭着这旋转，这轮回，伴随着旧的毁灭与新的降生，完成它的一次又一次舞蹈吧。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43cb7d0e0a243d4fc1b3c.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;大地颤动着，似乎要吞噬伫立其上的一切：高耸的楼台，抑或青翠的密林，酣然的沉睡，抑或迷途的心。一切都被某种不可抗拒的力量禁锢，拉入一种更原始、更未经分化的状态。这是多元现象世界的塌落，是于虚无中走向统一的深渊。『混沌』是人类赋予它的名字。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="哲学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%93%B2%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="随笔" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E7%AC%94/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>结合荣格认知功能对心理受困状态的思考</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/04/21/the-psychological-state-of-being-trapped%20copy/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/04/21/the-psychological-state-of-being-trapped%20copy/</id>
    <published>2023-04-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43c23d0e0a243d4fc1b2e.webp"></p><h4 id="关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应"><a href="#关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应" class="headerlink" title="关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应"></a>关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应</h4><h4 id="以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论"><a href="#以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论" class="headerlink" title="以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论"></a>以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论</h4><p>人居于“受困”的处境，就好像于柏拉图的山洞寓言中凝视烛灯投影，将其奉为「真实」全部之人，只能在黑暗中摸索着洞穴的岩壁兜兜转转，而忘记了一个更广的世界的可能。</p><span id="more"></span><p>在这时，最鼓舞人心的词大概会是“超越”（transcendence），也即那第一个决定走出洞穴去拥抱阳光与更广阔天空的人所到达的境界。这里的“超越”，不单单是指对于当下所处或者基于过去所拟造的境遇的超越，同时也是对于“自我”（ego consciousness）的超越与扩张，是一次属于过去自己的小小死亡，也是一次属于活在当下与未来无数可能性中自己的崭新降生。而对于 INFP 而言，由于狭义的 Si 所聚焦的「过去经验」与 Fi 所提供的「内在价值判断与构筑」能力的相互作用影响（此处狭义的 Si 是指取了 Si 的来源之一，也即更为「个人」的来源，根据 Carl Jung 在 Psychological Types 中所定义的 Si —— “subjective perceptions which orientate his consciousness in accordance with an archaic reality”，Si 的来源至少可以大致分为两种 —— 个人的与人类的，其中基于人类过去所构筑的内在感知提供的视角是更为「原型」的一种认知世界的方式），有时会因为过去经历的一些造成不良心理效应的事件而产生一种“受困感”（虽然很显然，这种来源的“受困感”通行于全人类，但 Fi-Si 的作用确实在一定程度上会导致相对更频繁地触发）。</p><ul><li><p>Fi 的发展与丰富：这一点的本质其实是培养内源性信心与尊严 ，也因此具有了一定的「存在主义」属性。「意义」本身最终不能也不可能由任何外部机构或个人强加给我们，而是要由我们自己去发现并定义。在认识到我们的生活本身就充满了无限与「意义」相关的可能性，并有意识地开始与真善美等能够滋养心灵的价值共鸣的时候，个人的存在本身就成了信心与自尊的强大源泉，此时的「个人」，已经超越了外界的各种评价体系，而是以一种“我美好地存在于世界，这本身即是很高的价值”的语境面对生活，从而获得源源不断的内在信念支持。</p></li><li><p>Si 语义的扩张：根据上面注解中提出的 Carl Jung 对于 Si 的定义以及其大致的两种来源可知，除了个人过去的经历之外，Si 还可以来源于「人类的过去」，此处的过去不只局限于狭义的真实历史，而是人类过去时代所创作的所有诗歌、戏剧、音乐、哲学以及各种各样的关于生活的痕迹的总和。通过有意识地对「人类的过去」进行探索与理解，我们得以更加广泛又更加细密地了解人性本身，与此同时也超越了只有「自我的过去」的狭隘语境，从而以一种崭新的视角重新认知周围的一切。在「人类的过去」里，往往包含了一种更为宏大的叙事，如但丁从地狱到天堂的旅行，柯勒律治在勃朗峰所感受到的神明，在这些叙述之中，我们得以找到一种更具滋养性质的 Si 来源，与此同时，也得以带着崭新的视角重新审视个人过去的某些经历，从而将与 Si 相关的「内在对话」转换 ，让 Fi-Si 的效应更具有扩张属性。</p></li><li><p>Ne 与外界环境：Ne 作为 INFP 的第二功能，与外部世界直接相连，其本身就具有一定的超越性质。当我们漫步于自然之境，感受绿叶在风中的微微震颤，仰望头顶轻如薄梦缓缓飘浮的白云，听到欢愉无比好似倾泻灵魂的鸟鸣，并用 Ne 将这一切与我们的存在串联在一起，就会发现，万物本身，就是相互联系的。没有人，或者说，没有任何事物孤独地存在于这个世界，所有的存在都相互勾连影响，构成了一张无比庞大的意义网。而将这外部的一切于内心世界相互联结起来的我们，此时的心，不也正随着微风、白云与飞鸟一起，自由地漂游于这世间吗。</p></li><li><p>Te 与暂时性优化：Te 作为 INFP 的第四功能，发动起来并不如前三种功能容易，但是 Te 在一定程度确实可以在更为现实的角度让我们走出困境。比如每日进行一定规律性的室外运动，以及学会充满效率地完成想要完成的工作，都是不错的暂时性优化方法。</p></li></ul><p>以上片段从四种认知功能 Fi &#x2F; Ne &#x2F; Si &#x2F; Te 的角度分别探讨了走出“受困感”的可能，通过一些语义的转换与有意识的功能调用，我们得以将原本看似的“缺点”转换为优势，从而拥抱一个更为圆满的自己。其实，作为一个 INFP 来说，最重要的，也许还是一颗愿意不断认识自我并超越自我的心，以及对世间美好之物的相信与热爱吧。</p><blockquote><p>后记：在表面上看，本文进行的论述也许只是在荣格八维框架之内进行的分析，但考虑到人类特定心理状态的共同性质，以及荣格认知功能划分的局限性，以上分析则可以看作是借助流行文化而进行的人类心理的普遍论述。作为行走于世间、活生生的人类，而非某种被抽象范畴所定义的存在，我们应该也必将高于诸如认知功能此类纯粹理论的框架。所以，在借助梯子攀登上天台之后，就请用涌动着生命与自由的眼与心，去观测自我与这个世界吧，相信在那个时候，“解放”会变得离我们更近一步。</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43c23d0e0a243d4fc1b2e.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4 id=&quot;关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#关于-Fi-Si-Loop-可能带来的负面效应&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;关于 Fi-Si Loop 可能带来的负面效应&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;h4 id=&quot;以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;以及广义受困心理状态的一些解决方案讨论&lt;/h4&gt;&lt;p&gt;人居于“受困”的处境，就好像于柏拉图的山洞寓言中凝视烛灯投影，将其奉为「真实」全部之人，只能在黑暗中摸索着洞穴的岩壁兜兜转转，而忘记了一个更广的世界的可能。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="哲学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%93%B2%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="随笔" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E7%AC%94/"/>
    
    <category term="心理学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%BF%83%E7%90%86%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Juvenalian &amp; Horatian Satire</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/05/juvenalian-horatian/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/05/juvenalian-horatian/</id>
    <published>2023-02-04T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4363bd0e0a243d4fc1a90.webp"></p><p>It is quite interesting to think about the motivations of Juvenalian satirists. The famous declaration made by Jonathan Swift, “to vex the world”, instead of being born from the simply attributed “cynicism” or “misanthropy”, ironically enough, actually originates from the innate belief in the possibilities of improvements in human society and the essential goodness of human nature. If one is merely cynical, it would make no sense at all for such fierce moral indignation, instead, one would simply shrug indifferently and walk away, which is exactly opposite to the vehement acts of a Juvenalian satirist, who is a true vindicator of social justice and liberty. Juvenalian satire is like the rallying cry of ancient prophets, full of energy and determination.</p><span id="more"></span><p>However, in my personal opinion, the employment of good humour is important as well, which can be considered one of the characteristics of Horatian satire, like the tone adopted in the mock-heroic narrative poem The Rape of the Lock written by Alexander Pope, for the “serious” pathway towards transcendence is spiritual enlightenment while the “unserious” one is light-hearted laughter; both have the power to dissolve the narrow confinement established by ego consciousness and lead us towards a more elevated and broadened view of reality.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4363bd0e0a243d4fc1a90.webp&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is quite interesting to think about the motivations of Juvenalian satirists. The famous declaration made by Jonathan Swift, “to vex the world”, instead of being born from the simply attributed “cynicism” or “misanthropy”, ironically enough, actually originates from the innate belief in the possibilities of improvements in human society and the essential goodness of human nature. If one is merely cynical, it would make no sense at all for such fierce moral indignation, instead, one would simply shrug indifferently and walk away, which is exactly opposite to the vehement acts of a Juvenalian satirist, who is a true vindicator of social justice and liberty. Juvenalian satire is like the rallying cry of ancient prophets, full of energy and determination.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
    <category term="Literature" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literature/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>论「自我」</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/02/on-self/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2023/02/02/on-self/</id>
    <published>2023-02-01T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.554Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43581d0e0a243d4fc1a69.jpg"></p><p>有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是月光洒不进的密林里幻化幽灵的追逐，是被其所困的牛犊下定决心找到答案的迷途，是元素精灵在毫无止息变化万千的暴风雨中的狂舞；有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是攀登出地狱的磐岩与烈焰之后重新瞩目的灿灿星辰，是在苦难之海漂泊良久的水手得以停歇的翠绿岛屿，是所不能及的无底深渊，也是一直在延展的遥遥远方。</p><span id="more"></span><p>「自我」难以被任何人类范畴严肃定义的原因之一是，它永远都在进化。这首与周围的世界万物一起谱写的名为「创造」的协奏曲，就像与一层又一层海浪相拥的细沙，留下了拥有无限复杂度的纹路。当我们在不断前行的路上，不再被「抽象」投射的阴影迷惑，并勇敢地摘下因为各种原因戴上的假面，其本质就会在「体验」中逐渐显现，这即是于存在与时间中磨洗并超越“我思故我在”所筑螺旋的 Dasein，即是对自中一切与其所视之物都表示爱与接纳的 Amor Fati，也即「自我」的超越。</p><p>如果我们仍能忆起孩童时的体验，大概会意识到，在那时，宇宙中的所有存在仿佛也都存在于「我」之中，但又拥有着他们各自恒久而闪烁的光芒，吸引着一颗小小的心不断去了解，去寻找，去发现。然而，随着时间的流逝与世事的变幻，那颗心仿佛也终于蒙上了「习惯」的尘，一切都变得熟悉而又无聊，甚至可憎。好在这些，终究也只不过是心的映像，是我们为自己所加的「叙述」，而不一定是事物的「真相」。所以，掀开那将「自我」与「世界」隔离的面纱，去拥抱，这一切吧。</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a43581d0e0a243d4fc1a69.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是月光洒不进的密林里幻化幽灵的追逐，是被其所困的牛犊下定决心找到答案的迷途，是元素精灵在毫无止息变化万千的暴风雨中的狂舞；有人说，他们见过「自我」，那是攀登出地狱的磐岩与烈焰之后重新瞩目的灿灿星辰，是在苦难之海漂泊良久的水手得以停歇的翠绿岛屿，是所不能及的无底深渊，也是一直在延展的遥遥远方。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="哲学" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E5%93%B2%E5%AD%A6/"/>
    
    <category term="随笔" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/%E9%9A%8F%E7%AC%94/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Dorian Gray</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/12/01/dorian-gray/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/12/01/dorian-gray/</id>
    <published>2022-11-30T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/6388b73d16f2c2beb19dec11.jpg"></p><p><em>The Picture of Dorian Gray</em> is a philosophical novel written by the Irish writer Oscar Wilde. It tells us that hedonism and amoral actions will eventually lead the tempted to decay and death without ever trying to tell it. Oscar Wilde wrote it without any moralistic intention due to his belief in aestheticism, which claims art itself is useless thus without any social implication. Bearing this philosophy of art in mind, this work destines to be a book of open interpretations, a book elevated or deprecated by the view lens adopted by different people, a world full of possibilities, just like every other great novel ever written.</p><span id="more"></span><p>The story revolves around a portrait of Dorian Gray painted by Basil, an artist infatuated with Dorian’s beauty. Through Basil, Dorian meets Lord Henry Wotton and is deeply impressed by the hedonistic worldview adopted by the aristocrats. After this encounter, the meaning of life is thrown into the dark abyss of void and non-existence; Dorian’s only occupation becomes the pursuit of sensual pleasure and outward beauty. But here comes the problem - beauty will eventually decay. So Dorian decides that he will give up his soul and make a deal with the devil, just like Doctor Faust. Because of this evil contract, the portrait, rather than Dorian, will age and fade. The wish is granted and Dorian pursues a life of amoral experiences while staying young and beautiful. At the same time, his portrait ages and records every sin that Dorian has committed, a discordant collection of crimes and decadence.</p><p>Apart from the novel proper, its preface is already a masterpiece by itself. In the preface, Oscar Wilde claims that “to reveal art and conceal artist is art’s aim” and “the highest as the lowest form of criticism is a mode of autobiography”, which profoundly points out the mimetic and reflective nature of literature and literary criticism. In Shakespeare’s plays, it is extremely hard to know what kind of person Shakespeare is; his religious, political, and even philosophical views remain vague for modern readers, shrouded in mystery. Because every character portraited by the bard lives his own life, in the glorious world of imagination; they reflect certain traits of humanity, and ultimately become humanity itself, concealing the artist in the this process. And when we are trying to read a book, we are actually looking into a dynamic mirror which tells more about us than about the book or the author. That is exactly why Wilde connects criticism and autobiography in such an intimate way. This specific view of art and literary criticism is essential to the understanding of the novel, for it liberates us from mindlessly condemning it as a book of decadence and decay merely because it tells a story of hedonism. By choosing to be free, we can delve deeper into its complex themes and probe towards the innermost part of our own soul.</p><p>In my opinion, this life in pursuit of sensual pleasure led by Dorian, is actually not a joyful life at all. Because it is totally devoid of meaning and only reveals life’s emptiness and absurdity in the end, when all the fleeting passion finally dies away. Lasting happiness, ironically enough, is not actually something we can consciously chase after, but the by-product of some other human conducts. It is not because the expectation of joy that makes us fall in love but because we decide to love and as a result end up embracing the experience of ecstasy. Our life is a hero’s journey, a lover’s journey, a journey which requires efforts and devotion, not some trivial funny games with the only intention of instant gratification. Just like Nietzsche said, “he who knows a why can bear any how”, human beings naturally crave for meaning, that is what makes us “human becoming” because once guided by the intricate and complex web of meaning, we are destined to embark upon so many fabulous journeys full of perils and presents; we can finally climb up the mountain of eternal joy. This is the happiness of maturity, of becoming truly who we can become in the end.</p><p>“All art is quite useless”, Oscar Wilde concludes his preface with this sentence. But is that really so? By reflecting upon the surface and symbol of art at the same time, by looking into the mirror with our deepest heart’s core, we begin to discern the great use of art, which might be unique to everyone’s experience and perhaps can never be made universal, but it will always guide us in the fierce storms and dark nights. “The artist is the creator of beautiful things”, and we, as readers, should be artists as well.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/6388b73d16f2c2beb19dec11.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Picture of Dorian Gray&lt;/em&gt; is a philosophical novel written by the Irish writer Oscar Wilde. It tells us that hedonism and amoral actions will eventually lead the tempted to decay and death without ever trying to tell it. Oscar Wilde wrote it without any moralistic intention due to his belief in aestheticism, which claims art itself is useless thus without any social implication. Bearing this philosophy of art in mind, this work destines to be a book of open interpretations, a book elevated or deprecated by the view lens adopted by different people, a world full of possibilities, just like every other great novel ever written.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Book Reviews" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Book-Reviews/"/>
    
    <category term="Literary Criticism" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Literary-Criticism/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>The Book of Thel</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/28/the-book-of-thel/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/28/the-book-of-thel/</id>
    <published>2022-11-27T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4313bd0e0a243d4fc1919.jpg"></p><p><em>The Book of Thel</em> is one of the prophetic illuminated books written by William Blake, a great British poet, painter and visionary born in the 18th Century. Crafted after <em>The Song of Innocence</em>, this allegorical poem is closely related to the loss of innocence, perhaps also indicating the creation of <em>The Song of Experience</em> in the following years.</p><span id="more"></span><p>The poem begins with Thel, the youngest daughter of Mne Seraphim, who separates herself and goes to the river. There, Thel laments about the transience of mortal life and the inevitability of death. The Lily of the valley, upon hearing her words, replies that even as weak and insignificant as she can be blessed by the almighty God and everything that lives should rejoice instead of complaining. Thel responds by listing the virtues of the Lily and compares herself to a cloud, dying without leaving a trace. So she continues to ask a little cloud about mutability. The cloud explains that transience is born out of Love and death is beautiful, for it means the transformation into a more romantic and unified way of existence. Thel responds with a lamentation upon her uselessness, fearing her only use after death will be feeding worms. The cloud says it is also a great use because it emphasizes the interconnectedness of all forms of life. Then, the cloud asks a worm to come to Thel, but the worm cannot speak, it only cries like a feeble infant. Soon after, a clod of clay joins them and claims even the worm is still loved by the divine. Invited by the clod of clay, Thel agrees to come to the clay’s home, where the couches of the dead and the fibrous roots intertwine. Wandering through this land of sorrow and tears, she finally comes to her own grave, where she is asked by a mysterious voice about the perception of the five senses. Upon hearing the possible woe perceived by these sensory organs, Thel runs back to the vale with a shriek.</p><p>In <em>The Book of Thel</em>, The Vales of Har are depicted as a paradisal place which resembles the Garden of Eden. Thel wishes to enter the world of experience and leave the innocent paradise behind. However, once Thel enters the world of experience, her heart is filled with terror upon the thought of mortality and the futility of human conducts considering the final demise is inevitable. But at the same time, her escape from all these possible pain and sorrow also leads to the inability to perceive all the beautiful things in the mortal life. Sometimes, it is exactly the transient nature of things that makes them more precious, like sweet music floating in the air and gradually dying away. In other words, Thel’s fear towards growing up is what keeps her from actually living. When she flees from the world of experience, she is also fleeing from the fullness of life itself. Innocence should take on a more elevated meaning, one found through suffering, through fire and frost, that Thel can never reach as long as she is gripped by the fear of opening herself up to risk. In order to truly become mature, one must face all these fabulous perils scattered along the journey. Our life is meant to be a hero’s journey, maybe unlike that of Achilles and Odysseus, but still possesses its own form of heroism. We need to slay the evil fire-breathing dragons, jump into the deep den of despair and rise up from the ruin of life all over again. Sacrifice and suffering are painful indeed, but at the same time also necessary to the completion of the Self. Passively accepting the given Innocence and Grace, may sounds like a state of extreme bliss, but are actually far less romantic than the process of elevation from the deepest pit to the highest heaven with the power of imagination. </p><p>“Fear ye not and behold the Creation of God”, a voice arises in the bottom of heart, retelling the story of Thel.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic1.imgdb.cn/item/67a4313bd0e0a243d4fc1919.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;The Book of Thel&lt;/em&gt; is one of the prophetic illuminated books written by William Blake, a great British poet, painter and visionary born in the 18th Century. Crafted after &lt;em&gt;The Song of Innocence&lt;/em&gt;, this allegorical poem is closely related to the loss of innocence, perhaps also indicating the creation of &lt;em&gt;The Song of Experience&lt;/em&gt; in the following years.&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Book Reviews" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Book-Reviews/"/>
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Death &amp; Rebirth</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/21/westwind/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/21/westwind/</id>
    <published>2022-11-20T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.558Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/637b82e816f2c2beb1b4b985.jpg"></p><p>This year, 2022, marks the bicentenary of Percy Bysshe Shelley’s death. Over all the two hundred years, countless fine lines of poetry written by Shelley have continously inspired people to rekindle the fire of hope. But of them all, a particular line from <em>Ode to the West Wind</em> may be the most significant one - “If Winter comes, can Spring be far behind?”. This single line of verse is far more than a rhetorical question concerning the change of seasons, instead, it is as the poet states, a divine prophecy given to those people trapped in states of despair and desolation. </p><span id="more"></span><p><em>Ode to the West Wind</em> consists of five cantos written in terza rima, originally invented by Dante Alighieri and first used in his grand epic poem <em>La Comedia</em>. Apart from the inherited rhyming scheme, there is another deeper layer of connnection between <em>The Divine Comedy</em> and this poem written by Shelley. Winter, like Dante’s Inferno, symbolizes death, while spring, the epitome of Dante’s Paradiso, symbolizes rebirth. Just like withered leaves blasted by the wild west wind are scattered all over the place to quicken a potential new burst of vitality in the upcoming spring, all those terrible sufferings Dante witnesses in Hell also lead him up to a more comprehensive understanding of Life, Light and Love, granting him the vision which enables the once lost Florentine to climb up mount Purgatory and eventually reach the gate of Paradise. Both of these masterpieces produced in Italy implies a universal truth, that descent is also ascent and death actually heralds rebirth.</p><p>Shelley embraced his own death two hundred years ago, drowned sailing in a tempest, but just as shown by the words engraved on his tombstone, a famous line from Shakespeare’s <em>Tempest</em> - “Nothing of him that doth fade, but doth suffer a sea-change, into something rich and strange”, there have indeed risen a thousand beacons from the spark he bores. </p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/637b82e816f2c2beb1b4b985.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This year, 2022, marks the bicentenary of Percy Bysshe Shelley’s death. Over all the two hundred years, countless fine lines of poetry written by Shelley have continously inspired people to rekindle the fire of hope. But of them all, a particular line from &lt;em&gt;Ode to the West Wind&lt;/em&gt; may be the most significant one - “If Winter comes, can Spring be far behind?”. This single line of verse is far more than a rhetorical question concerning the change of seasons, instead, it is as the poet states, a divine prophecy given to those people trapped in states of despair and desolation. &lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Poetry" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Poetry/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>Frankenstein</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/12/frankenstein/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/11/12/frankenstein/</id>
    <published>2022-11-11T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.546Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/63770c9616f2c2beb10859dc.jpg"></p><p><em>Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus</em>, which is now regarded as the first true science-fiction and one of the most influential English novels ever produced, was in fact initially written for a ghost story competition upheld by Percy Shelley, Lord Byron and Mary Godwin on the shores of Lake Geneva. </p><span id="more"></span><p>It tells the story of Victor Frankenstein, a highly-intellectual and ambitious scientist obsessed with the possiblities of imparting life to non-living matters and manages to create a humanoid out of the shattered and lifeless parts of human body. Yet, this life-giving process proves to be nothing like the joyous and glorious creation tale of God but merely a herald of unbearable grief and immense sorrow. This creature, abandoned by his cruel creator, knowing nothing about the world around him, decides to embark upon a journey to seek for love and warmth, like a newly-born infant who naturally yearns for the sweet milk of life. But the road ahead is destined to be full of poisonous thorns thanks to his monstrous appearance. The cold scorn and harsh beating of people finally tear his wings of hope asunder and drive him down to the deepest pit of hell, where only hatred reigns. The unquenchable fire of revenge burns fiercely in his bosom. He becomes a murderer and the last victim will be his own creator. And Victor, after witnessing the horrible deeds his creation has done to his family, especially his bride Elizabeth, also decides to seek for a righteous revenge. He must make his own creation perish. The cycle of vengence thus began, which must end in tragedy.</p><p>As readers, we cannot help but to reflect and ask: what on earth leads to the final tragedy of Frankenstein? If we try to follow the chains of complex causality and arrive at the very beginning of this creation tale, the scene of Victor maddening himself with piles of books must have reminded us of another similar figure - Doctor Faust portrayed by Goethe. Both of them are extemely intelligent and eager to know the ultimate mysteries of life. With this almost overwhelming intellectual power, they decide to challenge natural order itself and become some kind of necromancer proud of talking to the dead. This is the sin of hubris, of eating the forbidden apple in the Garden of Eden. Like Icarus riding through the firmament on his father’s chariot, or Ulysses travelling across the Mediterranean without the invocation of the Gods, Victor tries to turn the inanimate things into animate beings, to make sentient creatures out of decaying bones and flesh, thus befitting the name of “creator”. As a result, his following miseries can be regarded as a sort of repairing work done by the natural order, serving as penalties for trespassing the divine principles in nature. </p><p>Another important cause for the ultimate tragedy is the lack of love between creation and creator. The so called monster is nothing but a deserted child, helplessly howling for the warmth of care and love. He is a mirror of other people’s actions and his lived experience makes himself drown in the burning furnace of hell. What he can perceive from the world around is merely hostility and hatred, even from his own creator, as if he was the arch enemy of the whole universe, the infamy fallen angel Satan. No wonder he feels so sympathetic when reading <em>Paradise Lost</em>, for he, now already fallen from the innocence of Eden, has lost all the gentle protection of his creator. He ends up holding the entirety of Hell inside his aching bosom, like Milton’s Satan, committing all those horrible crimes. It is so true that mutual hatred builds Hell within while Love elevates the soul to the gate of Heaven. </p><p>The tale of Frankenstein speaks of two angels fallen from grace - Victor and his creation. Upon the barren crags of the fallen world, nothing but bleak coldness remains, sans heat, sans light. So, what is the real meaning of the creation of life? It is not  meant to be a mechanical process which can be imitated with scientific methods, but an interwoven web of Love and Meaning which is so intricate and mysterious.</p>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://pic.imgdb.cn/item/63770c9616f2c2beb10859dc.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Frankenstein; or, The Modern Prometheus&lt;/em&gt;, which is now regarded as the first true science-fiction and one of the most influential English novels ever produced, was in fact initially written for a ghost story competition upheld by Percy Shelley, Lord Byron and Mary Godwin on the shores of Lake Geneva. &lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Book Reviews" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Book-Reviews/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>会饮篇  Symposium</title>
    <link href="http://raptazure.github.io/2022/08/19/symposium/"/>
    <id>http://raptazure.github.io/2022/08/19/symposium/</id>
    <published>2022-08-18T16:00:00.000Z</published>
    <updated>2025-02-21T10:23:38.557Z</updated>
    
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="https://cdn.britannica.com/65/237365-138-03A2AF7F/did-you-know-The-School-of-Athens-Raphael.jpg?w=800&h=450&c=crop"></p><h3 id="作者引入"><a href="#作者引入" class="headerlink" title="作者引入"></a>作者引入</h3><p>柏拉图，古希腊哲学家，欧洲第一所高等学府 Academy 的创建者，柏拉图主义的奠基人，对西方哲学与宗教产生了巨大影响。他发明了对话体的写作方式，将哲学的问询紧密地融于日常的对话里，在一次次与其他灵魂的交流、向自己灵魂深探的过程中，柏拉图的思维得以与宇宙万物的理性共鸣：在形而上学领域，他创造性地提出了形式理论（theory of forms）和灵魂不朽论（immortality of the soul）；在认识论领域，他将知识与观点对比，提出知识并不是由五感获取的，而是来自于神圣的视野；他将由自己形而上学和认识论得出的结论延伸到政治和教育，做出了大名鼎鼎的拥立哲学王（philosophy kings）和放逐诗人（banishment of the poets）的决定。在这 2500 年的时间里，这些观点在质疑与探寻中不断发展，为西方文明甚至世界文明不断提供着崭新的观察与理解世界的棱镜。</p><span id="more"></span><blockquote><p>Plato is philosophy, and philosophy, Plato. - American writer Emerson</p><p>The safest general characterization of the European philosophical tradition is that it consists of a series of footnotes to Plato. - Whitehead (Process Phil)</p></blockquote><h3 id="话题引入"><a href="#话题引入" class="headerlink" title="话题引入"></a>话题引入</h3><ul><li><p>山洞里的烛火将稀缺的温暖投射，人们以为眼前那跃动的阴影即是真实，为此将传递真理日光的使者嘲笑（山洞寓言）。</p></li><li><p>诗人的口中流咏出不朽的乐句，那是神圣的占据与传递，就像一块磁石，将听众的心紧紧吸引（伊安篇）。</p></li><li><p>酒香飘溢，诗琴鸣响，在公元前 416 年雅典的一场宴席上，关于「爱」的讨论正如爱本身一样超越了时间的存在，抵达了永恒。这关于生命中最重要话题之一的讨论，为无数的后来人提供着崭新的视野。而这，就是今天我们要聊的「会饮篇」。</p></li></ul><h3 id="会饮之前的爱"><a href="#会饮之前的爱" class="headerlink" title="会饮之前的爱"></a>会饮之前的爱</h3><ul><li><p>看到「爱」这个字的第一想法大概会是「爱情」吧，那里会有两个人之间相依相持的甜蜜，但也会有占有欲导致的不满与猜忌，会有为了一个人赴汤蹈火的勇气，但也会有被激情冲昏头脑后的悲剧。人们歌唱爱情时，一半是「一次就好」里单纯的祈愿与憧憬，一半是「分手快乐」里苦涩的心痛与遗憾；人们演绎爱情时，一半是「仲夏夜之梦」里团圆的美满，一半是「罗密欧与朱丽叶」里破灭的挽歌。在这个角度看，「爱」似乎是一个亦好亦坏的角色，即可以将生活中的阳光万丈带到我们面前，又可以将生命本身的存在摧残至尽。爱，似乎同时具有「使扩张」与「使收缩」的属性，但不管他选择扮演哪种角色，总是将人们的心紧紧抓牢不肯放掉，嗯，「爱神」真是个奇怪的神明呢。</p></li><li><p>之后，应该会想到「亲情」吧，亲人之间的爱，由血缘的纽带紧紧相连，也因此更多了一份责任与义务，多了一份感恩与敬意。之后，应该会想到「友情」吧，跨越无数错综复杂的因果链相遇在这个世界，大概本身就是一种世界之「爱」的表现形式。之后，大概会想到对一件事物的爱吧，那样值得执着而专注地将生命奉献的事情，一定是重要到可以称之为「爱」的程度了吧。</p></li><li><p>然而，想到这里，不禁会问，这就是「爱」的全部了吗？这个贯穿在人类文明史中几千年的表达，并仍然生气盎然地在人们心中涌动的词语，真的可以这么简单地说清楚吗？</p></li><li><p>俗话说，“疑惑是理解的第一步”，不如就让我们带着关于「爱」的疑问，一起来看看今天的主角 —— 「会饮篇」里的讨论吧。</p></li></ul><h3 id="关于爱的讨论"><a href="#关于爱的讨论" class="headerlink" title="关于爱的讨论"></a>关于爱的讨论</h3><h4 id="Phaidros（斐德罗）"><a href="#Phaidros（斐德罗）" class="headerlink" title="Phaidros（斐德罗）"></a>Phaidros（斐德罗）</h4><ul><li><p>Phaidros 的谈话通过引用古希腊历史学家 Hesiod 等人的看法 —— “爱神 Eros 是最古老的神”而开始。爱神赐福于心怀爱意之人，激励着他们不断去做光荣之事，赢得爱人的欣赏。心中有爱的人们更有勇气在战场上奋勇杀敌，甚至不惜牺牲自己。Phaidros 的谈话以重申自己的看法作结 —— 爱是最古老的神之一，同时也是最受尊敬，最强大的神，他唤醒人们心底追寻荣耀和幸福的勇气，同时，为爱而牺牲自己会换来众神的嘉许。</p></li><li><p>斐德罗的抱怨与会饮的复兴： “我实际上读过一位有造诣的作者写的书，说应当赞美盐的有用性！人们怎么能去关心这些微不足道的事情，却从不去写一篇恰当的颂歌赞美爱？人们怎么能够无视一位如此伟大的神？” 有时，人们的视野会被日常生活的一些事物所束缚，只看见地上布满灰尘的六便士，而忘记了流动其上的宁静而神秘的月辉。这样的视野，是人们以不当方式追求安全感而为自己铸造的牢狱，是忘记了生命本真气息后的匆忙与无助。而苏格拉底一行人的会饮，正是对「交流重要之事」的呼吁。在当今时代，small talk 似乎已经成为一种风尚，这当然自有其好处，在一些简单普通的话语里蕴含了人情和些许关怀，但是，人类的交流不可止步于此，我们应该去谈论「爱」，去谈论「死亡」，去谈论「人性」，去在对话的过程中感受灵魂的交织与升华。当今社会的发展，趋向于「广度」的无限延展，而在某种程度上忽略了「深度」，其结果则是人们对信息量的不断追求与不可避免的内心的空虚。试想一下，如果我们可以迎来苏格拉底式会饮的复兴，闲暇之余，邀上三五好友，举杯围坐，伴着清雅的乐音，畅谈灵魂深处对于「生活」的认知，该是一件多么美好和丰满的事呢。然而，追求「深度」并不意味着对于广度空间所蕴含的“微不足道之物”的轻视与嘲笑，毕竟，「万物皆有其深度」，而认识到这点，则是一切人类真诚理解的开始。</p></li><li><p>斐德罗论爱与牺牲： “还有，无人会为你而死，除了你的爱人。” 斐德罗通过讲述阿尔克提斯、奥菲斯、阿克琉斯与爱的故事，指出了为爱而牺牲自己可以获得众神的祝福，而不敢迈出这一步的人，则会受到责罚。如果我们戴上「象征」的棱镜进行理解，那么，为爱而牺牲不一定非要代表着「放弃生命」，还可以象征着「自我的消解」，也即 ego death。从这个角度来看，「爱」的确是可以让人们突破自我狭隘躯壳，而去拥抱一个更广世界的强大力量，而这也是其能如此有效地改变一个人的深层原因。所以，在诚挚的「爱」里，必然包含着一次次自我的死亡与重建，没有勇气为了爱去牺牲自我的人，便不会看到由爱所导向的那个更宽阔丰满的世界，也由此不会迎来自我的新生。而这场心中有爱，遍历寒冰烈火的重生之旅，就是我所理解的「众神的嘉奖」。</p></li></ul><h4 id="Pausanias（鲍萨尼亚）"><a href="#Pausanias（鲍萨尼亚）" class="headerlink" title="Pausanias（鲍萨尼亚）"></a>Pausanias（鲍萨尼亚）</h4><ul><li><p>鲍萨尼亚作为宴席里的法律专家，引入了两种不同的爱，一种是「属天的阿佛洛狄忒」，基于智慧的交流，是爱更长久更崇高的形式；一种是「普通的阿佛洛狄忒」，基于欲望的满足，是爱更普通的形式。之后，他分析了不同城邦对于同性恋的态度，并指出雅典的行为法更推崇「属天的阿佛洛狄忒」，也即灵魂之爱。最后，他指出，爱的最终价值在于驱使有爱之人去追寻美德，从而变得高尚。</p></li><li><p>鲍萨尼亚的概念分析 —— 论不同的爱： 爱和阿佛洛狄忒是不可分割的。由于实际上有两位叫这个名字的女神，因此有两种爱。 就像维特根斯坦在「哲学研究」中所指出的那样，在对一个概念进行哲学讨论的时候，由于人类语言的模糊性与语境性，首先要做的是确定“这个概念到底是指什么”。在这里，鲍萨尼亚就很好地为我们展示了对于「爱」概念本身的辨析将会极大地促进理解的进程，同时对于「爱」不同维度与特质的分析也会使论证更加清晰和条理。世界上可以称之为「爱」的千万种情感与表现，自然不可以一概而论，对于它们之间的千差万别，最好的做法就是选择其中的一些特质进行讨论，就像鲍萨尼亚的「属天」与「普通」一样。</p></li><li><p>鲍萨尼亚的细化 —— 行为本无善恶： 考虑一下行为本身，可以认为行为本身无善恶之分，无高尚可耻之分。拿我们自己来举例。我们已经在喝酒、唱歌、谈话之间做了选择。现在，就其本身而言，这些行为没有哪一种行为比其他行为更好；行为带来的后果完全取决于它如何实施。 在这里，鲍萨尼亚指出行为的好坏不取决于其本身，而取决于其如何实施，拿出「行为」的众多构成要素中「如何实施」这一要素，是一个「细化」的过程，是思维进程中的重要一环，与上面的「概念分析」有异曲同工之妙。它使人们摆脱认知惯性的束缚，使思维更加深入到事物的关键，使想法更加复杂细微。而这一方法的运用可以解决很多分歧，比如，在某两所大学的辩论中，讨论了类似“金钱是好还是坏”的问题，然而，如果我们能进行足够的细化，就会发现这个问题也许并没有多大讨论的价值，因为双方不过是看到了对金钱的不同使用方式，而其本身作为一种价值抽象，是无所谓善恶的。在如今这个多样化的现代社会，面对因人与人表层观念不同而产生的种种本无所谓的纷争，记得「细化」的智慧提醒着我们，literalism leads to schism, and nuanced thought beats them all。</p></li></ul><h4 id="Eryximachus（厄律克西马库）"><a href="#Eryximachus（厄律克西马库）" class="headerlink" title="Eryximachus（厄律克西马库）"></a>Eryximachus（厄律克西马库）</h4><ul><li><p>厄律克西马库称爱影响着宇宙中的一切，包括所有的植物和动物，他认为「爱神」不仅仅指引着一切人类的事务，还指引着一切神圣的运作。作为一个医学专家，他在对「爱」的描述中也使用了相关词汇：在人类的身体中可以出现两种爱，一种是健康的，另一种是不健康的 —— 当爱可以调和两极，比如使热与寒、湿与旱的对立势力保持平衡的时候，也即「使和谐」之时，就是其健康的表现形式。他指出，爱主管着医药、音乐与天文学，可以治愈伤痛，爱让人与人、人与神之间建立起联系。</p></li><li><p>厄律克西马库对「爱」的扩展 —— 指引万物生成： 爱并非仅仅发生在人的灵魂与肉体中，而是一种非常广泛的现象。它肯定在动物王国中发生，甚至也在植物世界中出现。事实上，它出现在宇宙的任何地方。“爱”是一尊最重要的神，他指引着一切事物的生成，不仅在凡人中，而且在众神中。 厄律克西马库对爱的概念进行了扩展，将爱与创造紧紧相连，也即「爱指导着创生」。由此，爱不再是局限在人类胸腔中激情与欲望的代名词，而是流动在宇宙万物灵魂中的创造力，是「神圣」的终极体现。读到这里，不禁让人想起中世纪哲学和神学关于「爱」的相似认知，比如但丁所著《神曲》的最终结语 —— “l’amor che move il sole e l’altre stelle” （驱动着太阳和其他星辰的爱），这种爱是神圣之爱，是指引着一切事物生成的本源。由此也可见古希腊哲学对西方哲学和神学的整体影响之大。另外，将「爱」扩展到万物，使「爱」具有了类似尼采所论 will to power 的类似属性，不妨也可以看做是一次关于形而上学的有趣思考。</p></li><li><p>厄律克西马库的职业棱镜 —— 从医学出发： 让我从某些与医学有关的评价开始 —— 希望你们能够原谅我把自己从事的职业放在首要位置。医生的任务是，调和最基本的身体元素，在他们之间建立相互之间的爱。 每个人都有不同的背景，都有从相应背景走来的理解世界的方式，都有自己独特的观察世界的棱镜。厄律克西马库作为一名医生，在自己的职业实践中发展加深着对「爱」的理解，由自己的日常生活引导哲学思考，使其不断丰富和更有意义。由此可见，哲学并不是冰冷的逻辑推理和遥远的另一个世界的“形式”，相反却是离我们的生活最近，只是不易察觉的事情。将个人日常生活的体验融入自己的哲学体系，不仅可以更好地赋予哲学以生命力，使其变得更具有亲密性，还可以以哲学为导师，来帮助我们更好地理解现实生活。事实证明，厄律克西马库的出发点是极具启发性的，是颇有成效的。</p></li><li><p>厄律克西马库论爱与和谐： 有一种明智和公正的、趋向于善的爱，无论是在天空中，还是在大地上，受到指引的爱的力量要大得多；幸福与好运，人类社会的团结，天上众神的和睦 —— 所有这些都是这种爱的馈赠。 通过讨论爱可以调节身体的基本元素、赋予音乐以和谐的节奏，厄律克西马库在将「爱」本身的概念进行扩展之后，最终又将爱的功用进行了扩展 —— 向善的爱可以带来万物之间的和谐。不管这些不同的事物看起来有多么对立，所处的位置高低有多么悬殊，之间的不和有多么激烈，相互的爱都可以带来属于他们的和谐。这为现代社会中的种种争端和大大小小的战争提供了一个看似简单但其实意义深远的解决方案 —— 去爱：爱可以带来相互之间的理解与包容，带来和谐与共同的发展。随着科技的发展和生活方式的改变，人们似乎忘记了一些非常简单却又十分重要的事情。现代社会的某些观念带来了人的异化，在高耸的钢筋水泥之下，每个人似乎都成了一座孤岛，而本用来建立联系的科学技术，有时也会讽刺地成为建立孤立的工具，在这时，请记得「爱」 —— 这样简单的一个字，却是引向一切和谐的基石。</p></li></ul><h4 id="Aristophanes（阿里斯托芬）"><a href="#Aristophanes（阿里斯托芬）" class="headerlink" title="Aristophanes（阿里斯托芬）"></a>Aristophanes（阿里斯托芬）</h4><ul><li><p>阿里斯托芬则没有采用先前使用事实与逻辑说明观点的方法，而是讲了一个关于人类创生的神话：最开始的人是“雌雄同体”的，是球形的，拥有四条胳膊四条腿，有两张脸孔。但是因为这种人在体能方面太强大了，而且拥有巨大的野心，宙斯就决定把他们的身体劈成两半。在那之后，每一半都十分想念自己的另一半，他们奔跑着寻找对方，并搂紧对方的脖子，直至死亡，看到这里，宙斯心生怜悯，将这两半造成了男和女，使他们可以生育子女。由这个神话，阿里斯托芬得出爱是人生来就有的，它试图使劈开的两半合为一体，恢复我们原初的完整本性。</p></li><li><p>阿里斯托芬的神话 —— 象征主义 这就是我关于爱神的讲话，厄律克西马库。和你的发言很不一样。如我前面所恳求你那样，别把它弄成一出喜剧。 与之前谈话者扩展概念和逻辑论证的方法不同，阿里斯托芬则是创造性地采用神话来发表了自己对「爱」的看法。神话，作为人类想象力的重要表现形式与人类集体无意识的表达（卡尔·荣格），对理解人类本身具有重要的意义。然而，要理解神话，就要去理解其中所包含的种种象征。因为不同于逻辑所强调的语境设置与语义联系，神话影响人类思维的主要方式是通过意象。比如，「球形的最初之人」中，其形状 —— 球形就象征着完整与圆满，象征着人类在陨落之前的形象；而「奔跑着寻找」则象征着人们经历分离之后对爱的渴求与追寻。正如阿里斯托芬所说的，这样的描述并不是一出喜剧（取娱乐肤浅的戏码之意），而是十分有意义的讨论，其通过神话进行讲述的过程，正是一次由非理性过程（直觉和无意识）得出理性结论的过程，是人类理解世界基础模式的缩影。</p></li><li><p>阿里斯托芬的「爱」与「归乡」： 如我所说，我们曾经是一个整体，我们的本性是完整的，现在“爱”就是我们追求这种整体性的名称，因为我们的欲望要得以完成。 阿里斯托芬由创生神话所得出的结论和基督教的理解有一些神奇的平行关系，比如：原初之人被劈开之前就是亚当在吃掉禁果之前，而劈开之后就对应着人类的陨落（the fall of man）之后，好在，神给了陨落的人类以「爱」，使他们能听寻其指引，接近原初阶段的幸福。而由「爱」所引导的「归乡」，就是地上的「伊甸园」，是「心中的天国」。不管是对哪种意象的理解，都告诉我们「爱」是驱使人们追求「自我完整」的强大力量，只有心中有爱的人才可能找到完整的自我，抵达灵魂的故乡。</p></li></ul><h4 id="Agathon（阿伽松）"><a href="#Agathon（阿伽松）" class="headerlink" title="Agathon（阿伽松）"></a>Agathon（阿伽松）</h4><ul><li><p>阿伽松抱怨说：之前发表观点的人都只顾着庆祝爱给人类带来的恩惠，而忘了给予这位神本身应得的称赞。他通过引用荷马的诗歌，指出爱神是最年轻娇嫩的神，向往青春与美丽，而且拥有漂亮的肤色与杰出的美德，擅长各类艺术创造，是一名好诗人。在爱神的指引下，人们可以取得辉煌的成就，并得到幸福。</p></li><li><p>阿伽松与浪漫化的爱神 —— 诗歌： “她步履轻柔，从不沾地面，只在人们的头上行走。”我突然有了一种冲动，想念两行诗来表达我的想法，是他为我们带来了“大地上的和平，海洋上的宁静，狂风暴雨的平息，还有甜蜜的芳香，让我们安然入睡”。 阿伽松则又换了一种载体来表达自己的看法 —— 诗歌，虽然和神话有相似之处 （都强调象征和意象），但诗歌又有自己独特的属性 —— 感染灵魂的美感与充满画面的想象。他借优美的诗句来讨论爱神之「美」，如此「以美论美」，让人们心中也随之泛起美好的情感，泛起朦胧的可以称之为「爱」的情感。而且，随后，他又补充道，爱神本身就是一名诗人，像这样达到的论述方式与论述本体的一致性，可以说是十分精妙的：一方面，人们借助诗歌提供的画面感，理性描绘出爱神的美丽形象；而另一方面，则通过阅读诗句，直接在感性层面上体会爱神之美。而这，大概也是阿伽松选用诗歌来描绘观点的重要原因。</p></li><li><p>阿伽松与强大的爱神 —— 阿瑞斯甘拜下风： 因为阿瑞斯没有征服爱神，而是爱神征服了阿瑞斯 —— 阿佛洛狄忒的爱，故事就是这样说的。被征服者比征服者更强大，因为爱神的力量比最勇敢的神更强大。 阿伽松指出：战争之神 —— 阿瑞斯，虽然能指挥千军万马冲锋陷阵，所向披靡，在爱神面前却也败下阵来。阿伽松所描绘的美丽爱神可以征服一切，甚至是最残酷的「战争」。对于这点，我们似乎在内心深处也都可以察觉，强大而向善的爱能让战争的存在化为随风飘烟，然而在现实中，人类之间的争斗却从未停止。在 100 年前发生的世界大战中，很多欧洲作家和诗人都在自己的作品中呼唤「爱」，甚至亲自走到战场上进行救援工作，想要将「爱」传递。但是，阿瑞斯却仍然肆无忌惮地将战争的魔爪不断伸展蔓延，将饱含「爱」的诗文包裹在漆黑的浓烟之中。由此可见，面对强大的阿瑞斯，人类必须要团结起来，将对美丽之「爱」的理解和实践进行到极致，共同且真心地呼唤「爱神」的降临，才能够抵御他的侵蚀。</p></li></ul><h4 id="Socrates（苏格拉底）"><a href="#Socrates（苏格拉底）" class="headerlink" title="Socrates（苏格拉底）"></a>Socrates（苏格拉底）</h4><ul><li><p>苏格拉底在对阿伽松的演讲表达钦佩后，询问他是否可以进一步审视自己的立场，并与他进行了一系列的对话。他问阿伽松：一个人渴望已经拥有的东西是否合理？此时的阿伽松想起了自己所说的“爱神向往青春和美丽”，感到自己思维的不严密。在这之后，苏格拉底讲了自己与狄奥提玛对话的故事，狄奥提玛指出：爱并非是神，也并非凡人，而是介于二者之间的「精灵」，爱本身既非可朽又非不朽，在一天之内变化万千。她问苏格拉底：引发爱和欲望的原因是什么？苏格拉底没有答案，于是狄奥蒂玛回答：可朽者的本性都在尽力追求不朽，而各种意义上的生育是实现此目的的唯一途径。有些人的生育表现在身体上，他们通过生儿育女来追求后代的记忆与永久的幸福；有些则表现在灵魂里，他们则通过创造性的技艺来孕育美德与智慧。为了加入爱的秘仪，人们要从爱一个美丽的形体开始，随着时间的推移将自己的热情延伸，转而去爱所有的形体，在此之后，转向对美丽心灵的热爱，继而转向对美之知识的热爱，最终见证美本身，即 the true Form of Beauty。</p></li><li><p>苏格拉底与「对话」： 所以我说，“你这是什么意思，狄奥提玛？爱是丑的和恶的吗？”但是她说：“注意你的舌头！你真的以为，如果一样事物不是美的，它就一定是丑的吗？” 在之前的演讲者分别借助逻辑、神话、诗歌来阐述自己的观点之后，苏格拉底又换了一种风格 —— 借助他标志性的对话。对话是来自日常生活中的交流方式，拥有平实而又旺盛的生命气息。对话的交互性使其具有循序渐进的推演方式，使双方基于同步的理解进程而得出结论，显得更加亲密，让人易于接受。然而，在阅读苏格拉底的一些对话时，可能会发现我们对于其提出的前置条件并不完全认可，这也就导致了随后由此得出的结论可信度降低。比如苏格拉底问阿伽松：“当一个人欲求和爱某个事物时，他在这个时候真的拥有他欲求和爱的那个事物，还是没有？”对方则回答：“他没有。至少，他好像没有。”然而，让我们仔细地想一下这个问题，爱一件事物的原因并不一定是源自完全的「缺乏」，也可以是向往进一步的「提升」，那么由此推出的“因为爱渴求美丽，所以爱不美丽”的结论就有待商榷了。而这种现象出现的原因，归根结底和产生所谓“误解”的原因相同 —— 人类语言的模糊性以及更细化语境定义的缺失。因此，当我们进行相对严肃的「对话」时，明确详细的语义就显得尤为重要了，只有这样，才有可能在对话双方之间建立起真正诚挚的理解。</p></li><li><p>狄奥提玛与「爱的精灵」： 他是一个伟大的精灵。一切有灵的事物，都介于神与人之间。他是来往穿梭于二者之间的信使，把凡人的祈祷和献祭传递给众神，把众神的诫命和回报献祭的馈赠传达给凡人。由于介于二者之间，他沟通整个天地，把乾坤联成一体。 狄奥提玛口中的爱是一名穿梭于神与人之间的精灵，在这种意义上，爱像极了基督教里的「天使」，他们都是天堂与人间交流的使者，是与不同意识维度沟通的桥梁。如果用更“科学”的眼光理解，作为精灵的爱，更类似于一种驱动力，或者叫做“渴望”，在这种意义上，「爱」有些像叔本华笔下的流动于世间的「意志」。此外，在以上狄奥提玛的描述中，也表现出了爱与和谐的关系：爱沟通天地，连接乾坤，使万物处于一种相对的和谐状态，这点又与厄律克西马库的观点不谋而合了。</p></li><li><p>狄奥提玛论「爱与不朽」： 有爱的人在追求善物的时候必须追求不朽。“爱必定企盼不朽。” 狄奥提玛讲述野兽为了保护幼崽可以忍受饥饿，甚至不惜牺牲自己的生命，而人在这个层面上并没有太大不同，因为“可朽者的本性都在尽力追求不朽”。通过留下新生命来填补自己死亡以后留下的空缺，一切可朽的事物得以保存和延续。于人类而言，这里的新生命可以指身体层面的延续 —— 儿女，也可以是精神层面的延续 —— 艺术。从古至今，无数心怀着爱的诗人都希望能借自己灵魂的鸣响将被歌咏者化为永恒，如莎士比亚的一首著名的十四行诗里写到 “So long as men can breathe or eyes can see, &#x2F; So long lives this, and this gives life to thee.” 纵使青春会消逝殆尽，美貌会不复存在，肉体会归于尘土，但献给爱的诗文将会永远流传，直至宇宙的尽头，万物的终结。而诗歌，由此就成为诗人为爱而留下的新生命，成为可朽者所追寻的不朽，成为在须臾之中的永恒。</p></li></ul><blockquote><p>不朽的使者，甜美的爱啊 &#x2F; </p><p>让这古老而真诚的理解 &#x2F; </p><p>踏过两千五百年的风尘走来 &#x2F; </p><p>再度生长在你我的心田 &#x2F; </p><p>一曲终了，余韵绕梁 &#x2F; </p><p>会饮将结，永恒已至。</p></blockquote>]]></content>
    
    
    <summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;https://cdn.britannica.com/65/237365-138-03A2AF7F/did-you-know-The-School-of-Athens-Raphael.jpg?w=800&amp;h=450&amp;c=crop&quot;&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3 id=&quot;作者引入&quot;&gt;&lt;a href=&quot;#作者引入&quot; class=&quot;headerlink&quot; title=&quot;作者引入&quot;&gt;&lt;/a&gt;作者引入&lt;/h3&gt;&lt;p&gt;柏拉图，古希腊哲学家，欧洲第一所高等学府 Academy 的创建者，柏拉图主义的奠基人，对西方哲学与宗教产生了巨大影响。他发明了对话体的写作方式，将哲学的问询紧密地融于日常的对话里，在一次次与其他灵魂的交流、向自己灵魂深探的过程中，柏拉图的思维得以与宇宙万物的理性共鸣：在形而上学领域，他创造性地提出了形式理论（theory of forms）和灵魂不朽论（immortality of the soul）；在认识论领域，他将知识与观点对比，提出知识并不是由五感获取的，而是来自于神圣的视野；他将由自己形而上学和认识论得出的结论延伸到政治和教育，做出了大名鼎鼎的拥立哲学王（philosophy kings）和放逐诗人（banishment of the poets）的决定。在这 2500 年的时间里，这些观点在质疑与探寻中不断发展，为西方文明甚至世界文明不断提供着崭新的观察与理解世界的棱镜。&lt;/p&gt;</summary>
    
    
    
    
    <category term="Book Reviews" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Book-Reviews/"/>
    
    <category term="Philosophy" scheme="http://raptazure.github.io/tags/Philosophy/"/>
    
  </entry>
  
</feed>
